<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Day of the Lord, or, Israel's retvrn with an humble presentation of the divine characters whereby this wonderfull day may seem very neer approaching.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D476</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26676</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09523438</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09523438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43449</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37292)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43449)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1329:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Day of the Lord, or, Israel's retvrn with an humble presentation of the divine characters whereby this wonderfull day may seem very neer approaching.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.W. for J. Crook,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Christ Church College Library, Oxford University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Millennium.</term>
               <term>Eschatology.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43449:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43449:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DAY OF THE LORD, OR, <hi>ISRAEL'S RETVRN,</hi> With an humble preſentation of the Divine Characters whereby this <hi>Wonderfull Day</hi> may ſeem very neer approaching.</p>
            <q>Watch therefore and be ſober.</q>
            <q>For Sions ſake I would not hold my peace.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. W.</hi> for <hi>J. Crook,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the Ship in <hi>S. Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:43449:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43449:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>HAd the fate which attended the Millenaries doctrine, been but as propitious as the Arguments were reaſonable, it had doubtleſs been receiv'd with a more civil courtſhip through every age, than thoſe contemptuous ſpittings and unhandſome purgings at the mouth, which now for ſo many yeers have entertain'd it. To wipe off all the ſoyl from thoſe Spectacles through which it hath ſo oft been miſrepreſented, would no way ſuit with the ſtreight-lac'd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of a ſheet or two, leſt I ſpend more paper in Apologies than proofs. One thing, however, will deſerve a peculiar reflection, to conſider that this Now-dejected Matron carried formerly ſo well-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd an aſpect, that the firſt three Centuries (by her very Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries acknowledgments) payd a conſtant homage to her Reverence. Let the eminent Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> aſſure us in the name of the reſt (though a profeſt enemy at the giving in this verdict) in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face againſt <hi>Champney. Of all that wrote</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for three hundred yeers, even down to</hi> Lactantius <hi>incluſively, moſt of them a vouch it, not one of them (as he could finde) contradicting or writing againſt it.</hi> I will not conceal, that through the wantonneſs of ſome ſenſual Goſpellers (the Gnoſticks probably, that ſcandal to the name of man) this beauteous flowr of Spiritualtie was early di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted into miſ-ſhapen apprehenſions, of moſt hideous carnality, and warp't from its original puritie by the groſs conceptions of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> and ſuch like bemir'd Fleſh-potts, whoſe minds were more dirty than the materials of their bodies: ſo that I muſt confeſs the expectation according to their unclean fancies, was but ſomewhat the more modeſt dreſs of a Mahumetical Paradiſe. Nor can I much wonder at the prejudice of my diſſenting Brethren, while I remember in how unſeemely a portraiture they are wont to behold it. Can any ſoul that dare lay claim to Chriſtendom incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb facs="tcp:43449:3"/>the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of a Roy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Bleſſed Jeſus bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th a ſenſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>leſtial? In a word. Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Scripture view is the firſt Act of Heaven to reunited ſpirits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> The incompara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion; The Myſterious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the All-glorious Lamb to his then lovely Spouſe, the reſtored Jew, and the completed Gentile; The Divine uniwiſting of all the holy Prophets riddles; The New Jeruſalem in her robes of Innocence; Our Redeemers final triumph over Sin, Death, and Hell; and (with ſobriety) <hi>Eden</hi> in her Sabbath-day-garments, where as many as are allowed the royal favour of that admirable Communion (for the reſt are abandon'd to the burning Lake) ſhall converſe in their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal principles of ſpiritual integrity, after an inconceivable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with beatified Saints and Angells; Briefly, An eſtate ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, purely ſublim'd from ſinfull and carnal feculencyes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together heavenly, though on earth. I will forbear to ſtretch the preface any wider, leſt the City run out at the gates, and only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe the Reader, how it hath been the Devills maſter-ſtratageme, through all times, to accoutre this glory in Antick diſguiſes, by the opportunity of which Legerdemain, as he cheated the Ancient Jews out of the true Chriſt, even while he was among them ſo he clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conveyd in Antichriſt upon the inadvertent Chriſtians. Now venture on me Reader through theſe inducements, (with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of brevity into the bargain) and unleſs the premiſſes be made firm before I part, throw me out too for <hi>Cerinthus</hi> his Antimask.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43449:3"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Demonſtrating, that the ſtate deſcrib'd in the <hi>21.</hi> of the <hi>Revel:</hi> is the ſame with that portraied in <hi>Jſaiah 60.</hi> and other places of the Prophets, of Reſtoring the <hi>Jews,</hi> and fullneſs of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, to be fullfilld on earth.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing hath proov'd more inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to this truth, than that ſome have raſhly undertaken to deſcend too daringly into its ſacred receſſes, and (by the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of their own fancies) to deſcribe particulars about it unwarranted by Scripture. Thus well-meaning M. <hi>Archer</hi> hath formerly beplum'd it with many unſuitable Ideas, rendring himſelf ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and the opinion queſtionable; upon this ſtock he drew on his head that Reverend, and moſt Religious Combatant Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> an Adverſary of ſo approv'd abilities that his very appearance in the cauſe eaſily everted the rocking foundations of ſo tottering a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick. It muſt needs be held for an inſobriety ſcarcely excuſable, not to reſt contended with general ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of ſuch a glory, which is no leſſe than a ray of that tranſcendent brightneſs of which the<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath adviſed us that tis not poſſible for the heart of man to frame conceptions. My method therefore ſhall be to preſent the ground-work of this excellency from the ſacred Bible, and neither adventure my ſelf, nor encourage others, to raiſe any private ſuperſtructures. Goe we on then in the Name of God to make good the propoſals of the Chapter. Tis evident our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators themſelves referr the 23.24. and 25. verſes of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43449:4"/>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. to the 19.3. and 11. verſes of <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 60. And in theſe already inſtanc'd we meet with one paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage as unlikely to be fullfil'd on earth as any in the whole bible, <hi>viz. The City had no need of the Sun, &amp;c.</hi> Which notwithſtanding its parallel in <hi>Jſaiah,</hi> to him that weighs the Chapter prooves undeniably to be meant no where els. The 26. <hi>v.</hi> of <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the 5. and following <hi>verſes</hi> of <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 60. And the laſt <hi>v. in Rev.</hi> to the one and twentieth <hi>v.</hi> of that in <hi>Jſaiah, Thy people ſhall be all righteous,</hi> compar'd with <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 52.1.</p>
            <p>But let's take the Ch. in order. The firſt <hi>ver.</hi> of <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. is exactly correſpondent with <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 65.17. which place in the Prophet, if any ſuſpect not to be accompliſht on earth, let him take level by the 21. <hi>v. They ſhall build houſes, &amp;c.</hi> with many other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencies of the context. The 2. <hi>v.</hi> in the <hi>Rev.</hi> of the <hi>New Jeruſalem prepared as a Bride adorned for her husband,</hi> anſwers <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 62.2.3. <hi>Thou ſhall be called by a</hi>
               <note n="[a]" place="margin">New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>New name, which the mouth of the Lord ſhall name. Thou ſhalt be a Crown of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royall</hi>
               <note n="[b]" place="margin">New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> adorned.</note> 
               <hi>diadem in the hand of thy God.</hi> And 4. and 5. <hi>v.</hi> of <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 62. Where Jeſus is called<note n="[c]" place="margin">New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared as a Bride.</note> 
               <hi>Beulah, i. e.</hi> married, as the margent tells you, &amp; God compar'd to the Bridegroom. All which moſt evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns that condition of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> when the Gentiles ſhall come into her light, as appears by the 2. <hi>v.</hi> there, <hi>And the Gentiles ſhall ſee thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="[d]" place="margin">Our own Tranſlators conſtantly preſume theſe paſſages of the prophets to be meant on earth, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the contents they prefix. <hi>Vid. Jſaiah</hi> 54. and <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 62. But if they point at the Jews calling, as I fear not to make thee confeſſe before I cloſe, then will (ſure) none imagine any other ſcene than the earth.</note> 
               <hi>Ergo</hi> to be effected on earth. See the like evidence in <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 54.5. <hi>For thy maker is thine hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> Stated alſo on the ſame time <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Thy ſeed ſhall inherit the Gentiles.</hi> Compare the third <hi>v.</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37.27. <hi>The tabernacle of God is with men, and ſhall dwell with them.</hi> For the word <hi>[He]</hi> is not in the Greek, which is therefore odly thruſt in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43449:4"/>by our Tranſlators, purpoſely to referr the ſenſe of <hi>[dwelling]</hi> to <hi>[God]</hi> and not to <hi>[Tabernacle]</hi> whereas both in the genuine meaning, as alſo in the Greek it plainly belongs to <hi>[Tabernacle;]</hi> ſo in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek. My Tabernacle alſo ſhall be with them, yea I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people,</hi> directly as in the <hi>Rev. The Tabernacle of God is with men, They ſhall be his people, and God will be their God.</hi> Now it muſt needs be granted, that <hi>Ezek.</hi> in that place treates of the foremention'd glory of <hi>Jſraels</hi> reſtauration to be perform'd on earth. Examine the whole <hi>Chapter</hi> dear Reader, and uſe thine own judgment, for thou muſt be try'd by it: And that by the <hi>Tabernacle of God</hi> in this inſtance is meant Chriſt in his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I am half perſwaded that upon examination I ſhall not paſſe for arrogant, in undertaking ere I leave thee (by Gods bleſſing) to demonſtrate. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the 4. <hi>v.</hi> of <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. with <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 65.19. treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>New heavens,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The voice of weeping ſhall no more be heard, nor the voice of Crying.</hi> Nay more,<note n="[e]" place="margin">Of him that wonders at the poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this, I require, how in caſe <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſinnd ſhould one ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration have made room for another, for 'tis evident death entred in by ſin, as alſo that the world could never have contain'd all generat together, ſo that divers acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg we ſhould have been removed by Tranſlation, as were Enoch and Elias. Why then ſhould that difficulty moleſt any in this glory, which (according to the judgment of the beſt age) reſtores us to the happineſs of that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we loſt in paradiſe? And peradventure, if the nature of Redemption be well examin'd, it may be acknowledged an honour very ſuitable to the nobleneſs of the undertaker, to ſet the body alſo in its primitive ſtate by the worth of his price. This I am ſure, (Beſides the whole myſtery in which the <hi>Rev.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uns pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel with the prophet to this purpoſe) St. <hi>Paul</hi> can never be underſtood without it <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19.20.21.22.23. Though I will not deny but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was of vain men may puzzle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t with very tough intricacies, if any be ſo head ſtrong to argue againſt what the ſcripture generally commends to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for a myſtery, <hi>vid. Rev.</hi> 10.7. <hi>The mystery of God, &amp;c. vid. Rom.</hi> 11.25. The return of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. Now if the apprehenſion of myſtery may check our w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntonneſs, I deſire to commend S. <hi>Pauls</hi> phraſe into Conſideration, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. the Redemption of our Body, &amp;c.</note> Death it ſelf alſo is taken away as well in <hi>Jſaiah Chap.</hi> 25.8. (handling the ſame performance too) as in the <hi>Apocalyps. He will ſwallow up death
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43449:5"/>in victory.</hi> Mark well the whole ſcope in the 6. and 7. <hi>v. In this mountain will the Lord make to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a feaſt of fat things, He will deſtroy the veil ſpread over all Nations, and take away the rebuke of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from off all the earth, &amp;c.</hi> Tell me, wert thou left to thine own libertie, could'ſt thou poſſibly interpret theſe things otherwiſe than of the reſtitution of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and inlargement of the <hi>Gentiles?</hi> And that St. <hi>Paul</hi> applies the text to the Reſurrection, 'tis no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than what thou remembreſt I promis'd in the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; nor do I fear (by the aſſiſtance of my Saviour) to make appear before I conclude, that the ſpace of this myſtery is the very day of judgment. As to the royall magnificence of this New-<hi>Jeruſalems</hi> buildings, from the 11. <hi>v.</hi> in the <hi>Rev.</hi> downwards, conferr with <hi>Jſ.</hi> 60.10.13.17. and preciſely with <hi>Jſ.</hi> 54.11.12. &amp;c: <hi>I will lay thy ſtones with fair colours, and thy foundations with ſaphirs. Thy windows will I make of Agates, Thy Gates of Carbuncles, And all thy bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of pleaſant ſtones, &amp;c.</hi> Which deſcription, both the words preceding at <hi>v.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Thy ſeed ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Gentiles, Thy maker is thy husband, &amp;c.</hi> and its exact correſpondency to other paſſages relating to this matter, evince unanſwerably that it holds forth the forenam'd excellency, and to be accompliſht on earth. Compare <hi>Jſ.</hi> 54.11. with <hi>Jſ.</hi> 60.15. I will now goe fancy as many evaſions as can poſſibly (to my apprehenſion) be found out for the ſubverſion of this parallel, and annex them as ſo many ſeveral labells to this Chapter, leſt the continuance of its length diſcourage any Reader (in a Truth ſo obnoxious to exploſion) who peradventure may be invitted by the briefneſs and variety of partitions.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:43449:5"/>
               <head>Doubts ſatisfied. Firſt, Whether theſe paſsages be not already accompliſht.</head>
               <p>But you will tell me that this ſtate deſcrib'd in the Prophets is dayly fulfil'd in Goſpel-inlargments ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in Jewiſh reſemblances, The Church being all this while the Spouſe, to which Chriſt is the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom and King. Nor are our Teachers wont to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it otherwiſe than of the Lord Jeſus his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all government over our Conſciences.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> 'Tis a ſtrange miſtake whereby the unhappy <hi>Chili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asts</hi> have been long traduc'd, in being preſum'd either to dream Chriſts royaltie to be ſomewhat other than ſpiritual, or that it hath not been hitherto exercis'd in his Church. As to any charge towards a carnal or earthly conception, my preface I hope may cleer me; And who ever ſuſpects us to mean as if Chriſt had not conſtantly reign'd, is groſsly miſtaken in the Notion of his Kingdome preſented in the 2. Chapter of Holy <hi>Daniels</hi> prophecy, where we find it protray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in its two-fold ſtate,<note n="[f]" place="margin">Lege. the one which hath been, and is now, &amp;c.</note> The one, what hath been, and is, now in agitation, under the type of a ſtone; The other, what is expected, (but on earth too, <hi>v.</hi> 35.) under the figure of a Mountain. The one to be ſet up In the dayes of the<note n="[g]" place="margin">Theſe (Doubtleſſe) St. <hi>Luke</hi> calls the times of the Gentiles Ch. 21.24.</note> Gentile Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies reſembled by the Image <hi>v.</hi> 44. But the other <hi>viz. Regnum Montis,</hi> that of the Mountain, not to be erected till the Image <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Monarchies</hi> were<note n="[h]" place="margin">Anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this world are &amp;c.</note> pounded into duſt, and diſperſt by the wind <hi>v.</hi> 35. <hi>Ergo</hi> of Neceſſity yet to be effected <hi>On earth.</hi> By this may eaſily be explicated how much of theſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly<note n="[i]" place="margin">Thus is the marriage in St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t action.</note> Eſpouſals is in preſent celebration, ſo much namely as belongs to <hi>Regnum Lapidis,</hi> the ſtate of the ſtone: But that there is a more plenteous hope (to which theſe prophecies referr) If Bleſſed <hi>Daniel</hi> can not convince, me thinks St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43449:6"/>expreſly makes uſe of a paſſage of that prophecy to which the 60. Chapter of <hi>Jſaiah</hi>
                  <note n="[k]" place="margin">Both the ſenſe &amp; mark which our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>preters af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix to the 20. <hi>v.</hi> of <hi>Jſ.</hi> 59. aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, that the glor. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the 60. Chap. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins at that place. But (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially) St. <hi>Paul</hi> warrants it.</note> clee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly belongs, to ratifie a future ingrafting of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and fulneſs of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> See <hi>Jſaiah</hi> 59.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25.26. The force of theſe allegations from the Prophets, is, I know, uſually refracted by applying them (as they ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to Goſpel-inla gment, allegoriz'd under Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh repreſentments, but with how great overſight, ſhall be the imployment of another paragraph brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcover.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the foremention'd quotations muſt be verified ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely of the Jews.</head>
               <p>I ſhall wonder if any impartial ſurveyer of the 36. Chapter of <hi>Ezek.</hi> from the 16. to the end, can imagine the contents to belong to any other than to very <hi>Jſrael,</hi> ſince 'tis the deſign of that place to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate this incomparable condition of her beauty (When <hi>brought into their own land, cleans'd from all their Idols, given a heart of fleſh, &amp;c. v.</hi> 24.25.26.) by oppoſing it to the Loathſome eſtate of their defilement <hi>v.</hi> 17. So that if the Characters of the 17. and 19. <hi>v.</hi> (<hi>Of defiling their own land,</hi> when they dwelt in it, Being ſcatter'd among the heathen, &amp;c.) muſt needs be appropriated to the Jews in ſpecial, how is it imaginable but the other paſſages of her cleanſing, and reſtitution (through this and the whole following Chapter) muſt of neceſſity belong to them in letter? There may be divers inſtances to this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, though I will uſe but one more, very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable indeed to the diſcovery of the <hi>Bride,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.15.16. <hi>She that came up out of the land of Egypt, and call'd him</hi>
                  <note n="[a]" place="margin">Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber who they were that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt Baalim. 1 Kings 18.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Baali, The ſame ſhe ſhall at that Day, call him Iſhi i. e. My husband.</hi> Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Jſrael</hi> in kind, and no way deducible to the preſent Goſpel-condition. Nor can the preſſure of ſuch texts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43449:6"/>be eluded by conſtruing them of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as a ſuccedaneous, or ſuccenturiated <hi>Jſrael;</hi> for St. <hi>Paul</hi> (you heard) affords us<note n="[b]" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25.</note> warrant to give verdict for the Jew <hi>in propria perſona.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far I am ſure we are right, provided theſe promiſes be not fullfild in the Jews former deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; To him that thinks they are, it ought to ſeem but reaſonable that he ſhould acquaint us with that time in which <hi>Jeruſalem was cleanſed from all her filthineſs, A heart of fleſh given her, and her ſtony one taken away,</hi> as is promis'd <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. the paſſage ſo lately urg'd. And 'tis worth the knowing, when <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jſrael</hi> ever liv'd together (ſince their revolt from <hi>Rehoboam</hi>) and were one Nation, not two any more: for ſo they muſt, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.22. &amp;c. free from Idolatry and all abominations,<note n="[c]" place="margin">Nay, and ſo planted in their own land as never to be pluckt out more, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity yet to be effected. <hi>Vid.</hi> Amos 9.15.</note> ſecure from the moleſtation and dominion of their enimies, brought with ſo remarkable renown from all the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of their captivity, that other deliverances ſhall be ſilenc'd at the glory of this, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.7.8. Yea and all this to happen to them in the dayes of <hi>Davids</hi> righteous branch, <hi>The Lord our righteouſneſs;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in our Lord Chriſts laſt abode amongſt them, They neither dwelt together as one Nation, (for I hope we have not forgot the then deadly fewd betwixt the <hi>Jew,</hi> and <hi>Samaritan,</hi>) nor free from ſubjection to their Domineering Enimies the <hi>Romans, Ezek.</hi> 34.28. much leſſe were they void of tranſgreſſions, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.23. but guilty of the higheſt Treaſon that ever the ſun behe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. In a word, if this ſtate (in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) be that of New-<hi>Jer.</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> as the next pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph will aſſert, we may I hope reſt ſecure till we arrive at the ſecond Chapter, where 'twill be prov'd that the <hi>Magnalia</hi> there mention'd begin at Chriſts ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming.</p>
               <p>But how after all this, if theſe inſtances from the Prophets aim at one thing, and that in the <hi>Rev.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43449:7"/>the former pointing at a Glory on earth, the later, in heaven? Affinitie in words, I muſt needs grant, is no conviction that the matter ſhould be the ſame; though truly it might be much wondred at, that ſo exact an agreement ſhould thread the paſſages of both places, and yet the things be ſeveral; but I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume this following anſwer may remoove the ſcruple; That ſince we are aſſured by <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. that there is a<note n="[d]" place="margin">May it not be proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the Myſtery here ſignifies the <hi>Jews</hi> conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſince St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo calls it a myſtery, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25?</note> myſtery declar'd to the Prophets, to receive accompliſhment under the 7. Trumpet, And that this we have here treated on is declar'd through the whole ſtream of prophecy, and to commence alſo at the 7. Trumpet, as the next Chapter ſhall juſtifie, I can no way imagine but that the glory now inſiſted on, is that myſtery foretold by the Prophets. This in the mean time is very reaſonable, that what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd to the Prophets ſhould be ſought after in the Prophets. In caſe therefore the Excellency be in both inſtances the ſame, and that the replanting the <hi>Jews</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſeems to avouch) we may be bold to conclude (for who ever ſuppos'd the contrary) that the ſcene of its performance muſt be on earth, and not in heaven.</p>
               <p>One thing is much to be taken notice of. Beſides the ſcoffing at this conceit 2 Epiſt. of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 3 Chapter, 3. and 4. <hi>v.</hi> (of which anon) 'Tis frequently predicted in the old Teſtament as a thing ſcarcely to be ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to by Fleſh and Blood, for that I am perſwaded you will grant may be intimated by that <hi>Epiphonema</hi> at the end of this very deſcription, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.36. <hi>I the Lord have ſpoken it, and I will make it good.</hi> But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.14. to this purpoſe, where the Lord convinceth humane incredulity, by a miracle as great as the change, and very analogous to it, <hi>viz.</hi> Of gathering the dry bones into a living army<note n="[e]" place="margin">By conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing that Chapter with the precedent one, 'twill appear that the aim of the prophecie points at the Jews converſion moſt directly, remembring what was formerly obſerv'd from the Characters of <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.</note>. See the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43449:7"/>whole Chapter, for it wonderfully illuſtrates this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Atcheivement, being collated with the other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets forecited. Lay together <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.35. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.21. with <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 60.15. (the Chapter to which ſo much of <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. refers) and tell me whether any man can judge them to point at ſeveral things.</p>
               <p>I will wind up all the attextures to this Chapter with a brief reflection on the meaning of <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. <hi>The Tabernacle of God.</hi> That by it is underſtood Chriſt as to his humanity, who would deny? that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders, Firſt, The Tabernacle in its principal part, <hi>e. g.</hi> The Mercy-ſeat, was the Type of Chriſt, whom therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. Which our Tranſlation renders a Propitiation, but it is the very word us'd <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.5. and there tranſlated Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-ſeat. Secondly, Chriſt is<note n="[f]" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.6.</note> expreſly called Gods Tabernacle, by the expoſition of the beſt Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, meaning thereby the Humane Nature of Chriſt, which the Beaſt (The Papacy) blaſphemes by his opinion of Tranſſubſtantiation, which ſhews forth a peece of Bread for the real Body of our Lord, and worſhips it for his natural Fleſh, In this very noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is that of St. <hi>Joh.</hi> Chapter 1.14. <hi>The word was made Fleſh and dwelt amongſt us</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> Tabernacled, the very word in the <hi>Rev.</hi> So <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19.21. <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, &amp;c. i. e. The temple of his body.</hi> As alſo in expreſs terms, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.11. Adde to all this, That by tabernacle of God in this place muſt neceſſarily be underſtood either the Lord Chriſt, or his Church, (I know the objectors will pretend to no other ſignification) But let them remember, that it is farr enough from their ſenſe to allow the Church a continuance<note n="[g]" place="margin">The Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of God is with men, and ſhall dwell with them, &amp;c.</note> amongſt men (<hi>i. e.</hi> on earth) at the day of judgment, the time, at which (in the next Chapter) I ſhall proove theſe things to expect their truth. <hi>vid. v.</hi>
                  <note n="[h]" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> If the words there [The lamb is the Temple] tend not to the ſenſe I lately applied [Gods Tabernacle] to.</note> 22. in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43449:8"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Proving, that new Jeruſalem, that is the<note n="[bb]" place="margin">I dare appeal to any unbiaſt mind that expects the <hi>Jews</hi> call, (as moſt I think do) ſince there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not to this day the leaſt ſtep ſet forwards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſo great a work, and yet that terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cataſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe accounted as at the door by many of very different principles from me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not moſt ſuitable to Reaſon, that this muſt be the manner and time of that grand tranſaction; for as much as the known means of converſion (through Goſpel-ordinances,) muſt neceſſarily require more time to a nation ſo diſpuſt, and under ſo divers languages (we may adde ſeveral Religions to, if we remember the concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant fullneſs of the Gentiles,) than I am confident moſt mens opinions can allow them to the end of the world.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Jew, and fullneſs of the Gentile, begins at Chriſts coming to judgment.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>AS in the former Argument was made appear, that the 21. Chapter of the <hi>Rev.</hi> (compared with the Prophets) deſcribes a glory to be fullfilld on earth, <hi>viz.</hi> The inſtauration of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and inlargement of the Gentiles, ſo will I now indeavour to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that the term <hi>à quo</hi> or commencement of all that excellency is our Bleſſed Lord Jeſus's next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the clouds to judge the world. The matter is eaſily decided to an Ingenuous Adverſary, by <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.2.7. where the Triumphals over the final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the<note n="[c]" place="margin">The Church generally teacheth from 2 Theſ. 2.8. that the Man of ſin, i. e. Dan. little Horn, is to be deſtroyed at the day of judgment.</note> whore, proclame the marriage of the Lamb to begin from that conqueſt. Now the Bride (the Lambs wife) is apparently the New-<hi>Jeruſ. Rev.</hi> 21.9, 10. This truth alſo appears by <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. Where this myſtery declared to the Prophets is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd its accompliſhment under the 7. Trumpet, which is moſt expreſly the ſound to judgment. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. Another proof of this very date (anſwerable to the Angels oath <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7.) is from <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. where the Heavenly voyces utter (at the 7. trumpet) <hi>The Kingdoms of this world &amp;c: This world,</hi> mark that. But how I pray can the Kingdoms of this<note n="[a]" place="margin">Juſtly anſwering Dan. 2.35.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:43449:8"/>World be intitled on him otherwiſe than by this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious tranſaction to be finiſht on earth? Again, Compare <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.14. where the ſixt Trumpet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in looſing the Angels bound in <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp;c.</hi> with <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12. where<note n="[aa]" place="margin">To aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us that this paſſage is rightly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, ſee the wonderfull ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor'd it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek.</hi> 39. trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Gods judgment on <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog,</hi> (moſt probably the Turk too) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows <hi>Jſraels</hi> reſtitution. <hi>verſes</hi> 9.22.25. And that all this is to be effected at the time here ſpecified, ſee the 8. <hi>v. This is the day &amp;c.</hi> Where <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>It is done,</hi> is a ſure badge of the final day compar'd with <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17. at the 7. viall. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>It is done,</hi> and <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare alſo the proclamation to the fowles, &amp;c: at the 17. <hi>v.</hi> in <hi>Ezek.</hi> with <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.17, 18. Certainly, one and the ſame conqueſt over the Churches Enimies, Antichriſt. <hi>Gog, Magog,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Euphrates</hi> is dryed up, <hi>id eſt,</hi> The ſixt trumpet ended. For if the matter of the trumpet were the letting looſe the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or overflowing of <hi>Euphrates</hi> (probably the Turks) then the drying up of <hi>Euphrates</hi> muſt needs be the concluding of the Trumpet, ſo much is evident. Now the end of the ſixt muſt needs be the entrance of the 7. Therefore the<note n="[b]" place="margin">Remember the glorious royalty of this buſineſs, every where through the Prophets, judg if it be poſſible that Kings of the Eaſt can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon any other.</note> Kings of the Eaſt (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt the <hi>Jews</hi> to impartial Readers) enter at the beginning of the 7. for to that very end is <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> dryed up that a way may be prepar'd for the Kings of the Eaſt. Compare <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. with <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. and St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30. From all which (mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reflecting on each other, as the margent informs you) it reſults by a powerfull conſent, that the time of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſeeing and mourning after him they have peirced, is his coming in the clouds. That Chapter of <hi>Zach.</hi> cannot be deny'd to be a deſcription of <hi>Jer.</hi> reſtoring from the 6. <hi>v.</hi> to the end, ſo that the 10. <hi>v.</hi> (now quoted) to which the 9. leades us by the Emphaſis of That day, muſt be granted to treat of their converſion. It will therefore be but equal that we either yield that day here pointed at to be the ſame with what the two parallel texts referr to, or els produce from the ſcriptures ſome other in which they ſhall ſee and mourn after him, whom they have peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Beſides, 'Tis obſervable, the word in both theſe texts of the New teſtament is the very ſame (though
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43449:9"/>others might have ſupplied it) with that which the 70. uſe in<note n="[a]" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 'Tis admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to take notice that in all the ſeveral expreſſions of that direfull Woe, by weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wayling, gnaſhing of teeth, howling &amp;c. in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this word is never uſed, (though in theſe three texts never alterd,) as if the Bleſſed Spirit had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this phraſe, leſt the meaning ſhould be clouded by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ſtain upon the word.</note> 
               <hi>Zach.</hi> and were it not ſtrange if the ſenſe ſhould be diverſe? may we not rather think that it hath pleas'd the ſweetneſs of the Spirit to chuſe the ſame word, purpoſely to guide us into the ſame expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation. For unleſſe this ſight of him were intended as an extent of mercy to them that peirc'd him, (<hi>viz</hi> That Nation,) it had not (ſure) been expreſt by Mourning but howling. Tell me now doth not, the Chriſtian Church conſtantly underſtand his coming to judgment by his coming in the clouds? for ſo Holy <hi>Daniel</hi> hath taught us to ſpeak (for from thence is the phraſe borrow'd) <hi>Da.</hi> 7.13. which very place (for the <hi>Rev.</hi> and other parts of the New teſtament concentre as perfectly with the Prophets about this Date of the atcheive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as about the thing it ſelf) in the 14.22. and 27. <hi>verſes,</hi> as it apparently deſcribes this royalty, ſo it pitcheth it at his coming (in the clouds) to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and overthrowing the proud horn, which is moſt aſſuredly<note n="[b]" place="margin">The controverſy about Antichriſt hath no way been more obſcur'd than by applying to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> man of ſin, and the Apocalyptical whore, that which is ſpoke of Antichriſt in St. <hi>John's</hi> Epiſtles. That by the Man of ſin, and whore, is meant the Romaniſt, I dare ſay is demonſtrated, by that moſt incomparable light of our Nation Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> to unprejudic'd minds. As for the Name Antichriſt 'tis never us'd either in the <hi>Rev.</hi> or St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo that 'tis the liberty of the Churches ſpeaking (not ſcripture appellation) that impoſeth the term Antichriſt on the whore, and while we ſtrive to ſquare St. <hi>Johns</hi> Epiſt. that way too, we intangle the caſe. For <hi>Rome</hi> denies not the father, and the ſon, 1 Epiſt. St. <hi>John</hi> 2.22. 'Tis moſt cleer therefore that S. <hi>John</hi> refers to the falſe Chriſts predicted by our Saviour for the immediate Antecedents of <hi>Jer.</hi> ruin, S. <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.11.23. S. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.21, 22. An abominable falſe Prophet, of which ſort being then in the world, and of great Note, <hi>viz. Simon Magus,</hi> beſides <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> and the curſed Gnoſticks, &amp;c. for there were many ſuch An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts ſaith S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.2.18. This to be his meaning appears by theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Characters from the context. Firſt 'tis propounded by him at that 18. <hi>v.</hi> by way of citation, and reference to ſome other ſcripture. As yee have heard, &amp;c. But 'tis no where els to be heard than from the Evangeliſts ſo treating of the warning peeces to <hi>Jer.</hi> deſtruction. The words Antichriſt and falſe Chriſt never occurring in the whole Bible but in the Goſpels and his Epiſt. Secondly 'Tis inſtanc'd by S. <hi>Joh.</hi> as formerly preſag'd by ſome other ſcripture, and now us'd in way of Argument by himſelf for an immediate forrunner of ſome laſt hour (for ſo the Greek ſpeaks) and as a plain manifeſtation that that laſt hour was then a running, foraſmuch as the Badge of it (<hi>viz.</hi> Antichriſt) was ſo viſible. All which things were moſt exactly verified (both as foreſpoken to ſuch a premonition by the Evangel. as alſo fulfill'd in the leud Deceivers of that Age) at the time of St. <hi>Johns</hi> writing theſe Epiſt. being hard upon the fatal accompliſhment of theſe truths, in that remarkable calamity which ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after came upon <hi>Jer.</hi> Now after all this, will not the intimation (I pray) of laſt hour be more naturally appliable to that deſolation (then at hand) than to any thing yet to be expected, it being above 1600. years ſince this was ſpoken? For though the laſt times (in regard to Dan. fourth Monarchy) are ſpoke of us, yet ſure the laſt hour (ſo long agoe mention'd) is more happily applied to a matter already paſt.</note> Antichriſt (for all our Synod an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations) as every ſenſible Reader may judge by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring his deſcription with that of the beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43449:9"/>13. So that here you ſee where St. <hi>Paul</hi> learnt (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Rev.</hi> was extant) that Antichriſt ſhould be deſtroyed at our Lords coming, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. I will ſubjoyn other Arguments by way of appendence, purpoſely not to tire the Reader with too continu'd a length of any Chapter without taking reſpite.</p>
            <p>As St. <hi>Paul</hi> was formerly our warrant, for apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe admirable glories, mention'd by the Prophets, to the <hi>Jews</hi> reinfranchment, ſo he ſeems full as cleer in ranking its accompliſhment under the contempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raries of the 7: Trumpet. I know not how it may appear to others, but I muſt confeſſe I cannot ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue the Holy Apoſtles Logick, as to judg that he ſhould fetch a Medium from a prophecy of the <hi>Jews</hi> reſtitution, to prove the day of judgment by, and yet not intend to lay the date of that Reſtitution, at the time of judgment, look <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.11. <hi>We ſhall all ſtand before the judgment ſeat of Chriſt; For it is written, As I live ſaith the Lord every knee ſhall bow to me, &amp;c.</hi> But where is it written? ſave <hi>Jſ.</hi> 45.23, being a peece that belongs moſt aſſuredly to this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the 14. <hi>v.</hi> to the end of the Chap. Compare
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43449:10"/>I pray that 14. <hi>v. There ſhall come over to thee in Chains &amp;c.</hi> with <hi>Jſ.</hi> 60.14. and give your judgment if they mean not the ſame thing, for ſo I am ſure the<note n="[a]" place="margin">Can any impartial Reaſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the ſtrength of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> (whilſt yet the True and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church of God) as is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident This truth flouriſht by, in their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; And yet ſo much mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the ſame ſort of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſes?</note> 
               <hi>Jews</hi> alwayes expound it; And however we through miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take are wont to affix a mark at the 20. <hi>v.</hi> of the 45. Chap. intimating a different argument, yet that the whole ſequele naturally appertains to the ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, let any impartial peruſer judge by the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine characters emergent from the context, eſpecially the very laſt verſe, (being doubtleſs, not an abrupt parcell of a changed theme, but the united member of a continu'd one) <hi>In the Lord ſhall all the ſeed of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael be juſtified, and ſhall glory;</hi> Nor is this the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly text where the Apoſtle pitcheth the <hi>Epocha</hi> of this admirable royalty at the coming to judgment. What leſſe can amount from 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1? <hi>I charge thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall judge the quick and the dead at his appearance, and his kingdom.</hi> See, A kingdom joyn'd with his appearance to judge the world, and yet not the final kingdom for ever in the Heavens, for after the univerſal reſurrection, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour reſigns up the kingdom to the father, that he may be all in, all 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 24, 28. That kingdom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which is neither before his appearance, not yet after the laſt reſurrection, muſt neceſſarily be conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between them.</p>
            <p>Who can but wonder that this Truth ſhould be ſo boggled at, which is ſo harmoniouſly accorded to through all the Prophets? <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5.6. <hi>&amp;c. In his dayes &amp;c. Ezek.</hi> 34.23. <hi>&amp;c. Ezek.</hi> 37.22, 23, 24, <hi>&amp;c. Zach.</hi> 6.12, 13, <hi>&amp;c. Zach.</hi> 14. from the 16. to the end? All which expreſſe a Glory to<note n="[*]" place="margin">It being formerly cleer'd that theſe things are ſpoke of <hi>Jer.</hi> in perſon.</note> 
               <hi>Jer.</hi> (evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to be meant on earth) to be eſtabliſht <hi>In the Dayes of their Meſſiah,</hi> or <hi>David</hi> their Prince; (<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> being dead long before theſe things were ſpoken) <hi>The Lord our Righteouſneſs is his name.</hi> But it can not be pretended that theſe things were fullfill'd in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43449:10"/>Meſſiahs firſt coming, for then <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> did not<note n="[a]" place="margin">We well know when they were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated, but 'tis hard to ſay when they met, unleſſe we make the ſending of a ſingle prieſt to inſtruct the Pagans plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Samaria,</hi> to be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the 10. Tribes from their captivity 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.27. 'Twill proove but a very pinch'd Synechdoche to cramp 10. Tribes in one perſon.</note> dwell together. I am ſure they did not dwell as one Nation, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.22. The Samaritan woman is a competent witneſs, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.9. Much leſſe did they dwell ſafely without moleſtation from their enimies, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.28. Therefore theſe of neceſſity (as the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the old Chriſtians expected) are to receive per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance at the Meſſiah's ſecond comming. You will not I am ſure denie but the ſame thing is promis'd in this place of <hi>Ezek.</hi> (and its complices) as in <hi>Jſ.</hi> 60. for that appears by comparing <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.21. with <hi>Jſ.</hi> 60.14, 15. Beſides, the whole deſcription match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in each place.</p>
            <p>The forecited Chap. of Holy <hi>Daniel</hi> is worthy of a ſecond ſurvey, being queſtionleſſe the ſacred ſtore I uſe from whence the deſcription of the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is deriv'd in ſo many correſpondencies of the New Teſtament, <hi>viz. That the</hi>
               <note n="[*]" place="margin">The ground on which the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment calleth our Saviour the ſon of man is (moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly) taken from this place in <hi>Dan.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſon of man ſhall come in the clouds; In the Glory of his father, with his Holy Angels,</hi> in reference to the 10. and 13. <hi>v. That Antichriſt ſhall be deſtroyed with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his coming,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> had foretold of the little Horn. <hi>v.</hi> 26. <hi>That the Deſtruction ſhould be by fire,</hi> it being ſaid <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>His throne was a fiery flame, and his wheeles as burning fire. A fiery ſtream iſſu'd and came forth from before him, &amp;c.</hi> And why (I would fain know) may we not bring hither St. <hi>Johns</hi> parallel from <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4? <hi>I ſaw thrones, and they ſate upon them, and judgment was given unto them,</hi> anſwering <hi>Daniel</hi> 7.9, 10. <hi>I beheld till the thrones were pitched down, and the judgment was ſet,</hi> and (<hi>v.</hi> 22.) <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was given to the ſaints of the moſt high.</hi> What difference (I pray) betwixt St. <hi>Johns</hi> [and the ſaints lived and reigned with Chriſt] and <hi>Daniels</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:43449:11"/>[The Saints poſſeſſed the kingdom] <hi>viz.</hi> with the ſon of man who came in the clouds? Think other men as they pleaſe, I cannot for my own part be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (conſidering the wonderfull twiſt of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment running through the whole ſcripture) but that this kingdom of the ſon of man, when the ſaints ſhall reign with him, and all people, nations, and langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhall ſerve him <hi>v.</hi>
               <note n="[*]" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>id. Rev.</hi> 7.9. <hi>All nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, kindred, people, and tongues,</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the ſame king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as the context and citations juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> 14. is the very ſame with what hath been ſo unanimouſly inculcated from the reſt of the Prophets, concerning the <hi>Jews</hi> converſion, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> inlargement. One thing, In the mean time, I think will ſcarce be queſtion'd, that <hi>Daniels</hi> date ſeems to be the day of judgment, agreeably to <hi>Jſ.</hi> 66.10.12.15.16.19.20.22. Where mention is made of the fiery indignation to be powred forth; The Glory of <hi>Jeruſalems reſtauration, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles fullneſſe, with New Heavens, &amp;c. in one and the ſame particular Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time we may I hope make a ſhift to ſift out St. <hi>Peters</hi> meaning, in referring his Readers to the Prophets, about the ſame glory, and the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement, <hi>viz. New Heavens, and new earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs, to be founded at his coming,</hi> 2. Epiſt. 3. Chap. 2.4.13. <hi>v. &amp;c.</hi> From which Chapter though ſome buſie heads may poſſibly frame objections to fruſtrate the expectation, raiſed namely from the conflagration, and diſſolution here mention'd, yet let them know that by the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, they muſt diſappoint St. <hi>Peters</hi> meaning too, who notwithſtanding ſuch diſſolution teacheth us to expect the accompliſhment of that myſtery mention'd by the Prophets of <hi>New Heavens, &amp;c.</hi> By which, if after recourſe to the Prophets, we find any thing els that can be meant conſonant to the other ſcriptures, than what I have hitherto inſtanc'd, I ſhall willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly retract all this for the advantage of ſo deſiderable a ſatisfaction. Till then may theſe following conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43449:11"/>be accepted as neither impertinent, nor te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſince he ſends us to the Prophets <hi>v.</hi> 2. had not (probably) an eye amongſt other Prophecies to <hi>Jſ.</hi> 65. from the 17. to the end, and <hi>Jſ.</hi> 60. through the whole Chapter, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>v.</hi> 21? The which allegations who ever ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from affixing them on the conſolation of <hi>Jſ.</hi> let him weigh maturely before he ſpeak, leſt his prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitancy impeach<note n="[*]" place="margin">See be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what was obſerv'd from <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 25, 26.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> as an acceſſory to his raſhneſſe. Secondly, Whether it be not rational to conclude that the Apoſtle at the 8. <hi>v.</hi> had reſpect to the common ſaying of the <hi>Jews</hi> (to whom<note n="[a]" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>id.</hi> his entrance to his firſt Epiſt. To the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſcattered, &amp;c. <hi>i. e. Jews</hi> diſperſed, &amp;c.</note> he writ) whoſe formal words of the <hi>Day of judgment,</hi> were wont to be, <hi>One day with the Lord is as a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years;</hi> rather than to the 90. <hi>Pſ.</hi> where the words <hi>One day with the Lord is as a thouſand years,</hi> are not, though the latter part of the ſentence [A thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years as one day] may allude thither? And who ſhould not ſooner judge that the ſame form of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, quoted by <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> (two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned primitive witneſſes to this truth) was taken from this Epiſt. of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> than from the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd <hi>Pſ.</hi> Foraſmuch as they likewiſe uſe it (as the Jewiſh Doctors did) for the <hi>day of judgment? Juſtin Martyr</hi> diſtinctly alleging in theſe terms, treating of that day, [we know that that ſaying. <hi>The day of the Lord is as a thouſand years,</hi> points hither. Thirdly, Whether the fiery devaſtation here deſcrib'd be any greater rubb to this hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> than the ſame intimation in Holy <hi>Dan.</hi> Chap. 7. and <hi>Jſ.</hi> 66. (where alſo the fiery vengeance is mention'd, and yet the <hi>Iews</hi> reſtoring moſt pregnantly avouched,) or than the tenour of the whole Bible, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ranketh this glory under the 7. Trumpet? Fourthly, Whether this wonderfull concordance of St. <hi>Peter</hi> with the reſt of the ſcripture ought not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43449:12"/>us that the coming of our Lord here mention'd (<hi>v.</hi> 4.) at which he<note n="[b]" place="margin">By com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the 4. <hi>v. Where is the promiſe of his coming,</hi> with 13. <hi>v. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> appears plainly that the Promiſe is fixt at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> pitcheth this ſtately change, is his expected perſonal coming to judgment at the 7. trumpet, and not his former vindictive appearance in fury at the deſolation of <hi>Ier.</hi> by the <hi>Romans,</hi> to which the incomparably learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> is wont to referr many paſſages of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which (my thinks) in this preſent text, the Analogie to other places were ſufficient to diſtinguiſh? Laſtly, Whether the ſcoffing here intimated <hi>v.</hi> 3. can be at any thing els<note n="[a]" place="margin">The time hits it well. In the laſt dayes, The primitive dayes being for it.</note> than this very opinion, ſince the Opponent, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Scoffer, diſputes directly againſt it, but the Reſpondent, <hi>viz.</hi> the Apoſtle, pleads ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely for it? See all this made good. The Queſtion in controverſy is about the Promiſe of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which the Millenary affirms to conſiſt in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible reſtitution. Againſt this the<note n="[b]" place="margin">It would be inquir'd, ſince the ſcoffers are ſuppos'd to be Chriſtians, in what other ſenſe (than which I have nam'd) can they be ſaid to ſcoff at our Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for as to his coming to judgment (in the general notion) I think never any Chriſtians did or will denie it; Nor can any imagine the Apoſtle ſhould bend his aim againſt ſpeculative Atheiſts, ſuch as <hi>Lucian, Diagords &amp;c.</hi> For who ever heard of can think that ſuch toothleſs Barkers as thoſe Dogs are, may be of any dangerous influence to well-grounded Chriſtians? ſo that upon that ſcore there had not needed ſuch carneſt incitement to remembrance and caution, as the Apoſtle here uſeth, which certainly muſt neceſſarily import the ſcoffing party not onely to be Chriſtian but very conſiderable too. As for the practical Atheiſt and looſe-liv'd wretch this text meddles not with that capacity in chief, For this ſcoffer deals with arguments.</note> Scoffer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects (ſo much light the particle <hi>[For]</hi> will afford us, it being a cauſal Conjunction naturally leading into an argument.) <hi>e. g.</hi> Where is this promiſe of his coming in ſuch a reſtitution as you <hi>Chiliaſts</hi> dreath of, what appearance ſee ye in the leaſt meaſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any ſuch mutation? <hi>For</hi> ſince the Fathers fell aſleep all things continue as they were; Tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous warrs ſtill, angry commotions, abominable lives, diſſolute manners, Rebellions, Treaſons, All things as they were; What hopes then of any ſuch change? I ſhould be unwilling to prevaricate one jot, but have I hope preſented the Argument in its natural
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43449:12"/>colours, being (for the ſumm of it) ſuch an one as (really) I my ſelf have heard from an ancient mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. But on the other ſide, The Apoſtle ſeems to me moſt confidently to aſſert it <hi>v.</hi> 13.<note n="[*]" place="margin">Adde to this text of St. <hi>Peter Act.</hi> 3.21. ſpoken alſo by S. <hi>Peter</hi> upon the ſame affidavit of the Prophets, and on the ſame pitch of time <hi>When the heavens diſcloſe him.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nevertheleſs &amp;c. q. d.</hi> Say the ſcoffers what they pleaſe, <hi>We accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his promiſe look, for</hi>
               <note n="[†]" place="margin">By obſerving the ſpeech in, <hi>Jſ.</hi> 51.15.16. of <hi>Jſ.</hi> deliverance from <hi>Egypt,</hi> it may (peradventure) be gather'd what <hi>the New Heaven and New Earth may imply. I am thy God who divided the Sea</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the Red Sea) <hi>And I put my words in thy mouth, (i. e.</hi> I gave thee my law) <hi>and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd thee with the ſhaddow of Mine hand, that I might plant the Heavens, and lay the foundation of the Earth,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Make thee a Kingdom or Common-wealth in the Land of promiſe) for in that notion Heaven and Earth are frequently taken in the Prophets. So here, <hi>New Heaven and New Earth. i. e.</hi> a New Kingdom, or New manner of Government.</note> 
               <hi>new Heavens, and a new Earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall we after all this be difficult to grant that this admirable circle of myſteries, (I mean this renowned Chiliad) is that which the ſcriptures call the <hi>Day of judgment?</hi> I will adde but a word or two to what is already ſaid, but (I think) from ſuch evidences as will hardly be evaded from particularizing the day of judgment, though they alſo determine this expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to that very day. Examine we firſt that famous judging of the Heathen in the valley of <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophat, Ioel.</hi> 3. from the 9. to the end, which many of our Divines, (farr enough from my opinion in this buſineſs) interpret literally of that <hi>Terrible day,</hi> foraſmuch as the 13. <hi>v.</hi> ſpeaks the ſame thing with <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.15. But that the <hi>Rev.</hi> in that text ſpeaks of the very time of judgment, none will ſure deny that views one like the ſon of man coming in a cloud <hi>v.</hi> 14. Read now on in <hi>Ioel,</hi> from <hi>v.</hi> 16. to the end, and tell me if this great good thing to <hi>Iſrael</hi> be not at the 18. <hi>v.</hi> affix'd to that very day. I know thou wilt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43449:13"/>ſhift me by the mark Pleading (I wiſſe) to a diſtinct argument. But I ask thee who made that mark? did not they who allwaies miſunderſtood the Prophecy? For that it is of the ſame contents with the 16. and 17. <hi>v.</hi> (where no ſuch mark appears, nay, where the Characters point directly to the judgment too) let our own reaſon (unleſſe we have a mind to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet it,) inform us; <hi>The Lord ſhall roar out of Sion, &amp;c. The Heavens and the Earth ſhall ſhake, &amp;c.</hi> Surely that Dreadfull day. <hi>But the Lord will be the hope of his people, and the ſtrength of the Children of Iſ. &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="[a]" place="margin">See <hi>Jſ.</hi> 60.21. which Chapter aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us of a performance for theſe things on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth.</note> 
               <hi>Then ſhall Jeruſalem be holy, &amp;c.</hi> We are wont to think <hi>Then</hi> and <hi>that Day</hi> aequipollents. Lord! That an unadviſed ſcratch with a pen ſhould be able to divert ſo cleer, and ſo powerfull a Truth. Another full as pregnant illuſtration of this ſenſe may be fetch'd from <hi>Zach.</hi> 14. Where alſo is the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that wonderfull day, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 6, &amp;c. <hi>The Lord my God ſhall come, and all the Saints with thee, v.</hi> 5. will certainly evince ſo much, collated with <hi>Daniels [Thouſand Thouſands,]</hi> Chap. 7.10. and St. <hi>Pauls [All that ſleep in Ieſus will God bring with him]</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. as alſo<note n="[b]" place="margin">Conſider whether the mutual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be not ſufficient to particularize the day of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2. to the judgment, though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Admirable Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> ſways much to the contrary, ſee the former Chapter in <hi>verſes</hi> 7.8.9.10.</note> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>[Revealed from heaven with his mighty Angels.]</hi> But what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows? <hi>In that day</hi> (<hi>v.</hi> 8.) <hi>ſhall living waters goe forth from Ieruſ. &amp;c.</hi> to the end of the Chap. Manifeſtly deſcribing that unmatchable glory and Indulgence to <hi>Ieruſ.</hi> where, yet, <hi>Holineſs on the horſe belles, v.</hi> 20. is I trow legible enough to intimate the ſtate to be perform'd on earth, and not in Heaven, <hi>vid. ſup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Antient <hi>Iews</hi> kept conſtantly up to this tenet, never underſtanding by the <hi>Great day of judgment</hi> (ſo frequent in their Rabbines, and deriv'd from thence by our Saviour and his Ap.) leſſe than a time of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43449:13"/>many years, yea, ſome (ſtrange to tell) punctually a<note n="[c]" place="margin">If the <hi>Jews</hi> be not reſtor'd till our Saviour comes (as is formerly proov'd) who ever imagind their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in this glorious ſtate of their reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an action of a few dayes?</note> thouſand years continuance, in which tearm they conceive thoſe <hi>tremenda Magnalia,</hi> through all the Prophets to be atchieved by the Meſſiah. Whence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at this day they look not for him, untill the Great day of judgment; So that every Thunder-clap ſollicits them to this expectation. Under this notion was the fam'd Millennium, beheld in the firſt three centuries, looking on this whole ſpace as the Day of judgment, and the myſterious ſabbath in which the ſaints ſhould reign with Chriſt the Lord. <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Irenaeus,</hi> and <hi>Lactantius,</hi> are (aſſuredly) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be reported after, amongſt whom the Zelous <hi>Martyr,</hi> in his dialogue with the Jew could in no wiſe forbear from faſtning the impeachment of Atheiſm and Hereſy, upon the diſſenting Chriſtians, poſitively concluding, that who ever were<note n="[a]" place="margin">See dr. <hi>Fernes</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in the preface.</note> in all points Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, embraced this contemplation.</p>
            <p>After all theſe premiſſes take I pray another ſhort view of that lofty portray in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and another parallel reference of the New Teſtament. Unleſſe the performance there deſcrib'd of the marriage of the lamb, and its appendant royalties, were the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day of judgment, how comes it (not onely to be a<note n="[bb]" place="margin">The ſpirit uſeth tranſitions into diſtinct viſions, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting variety, <hi>e.g.</hi> After theſe things, Chap. 7.1. after this Chap. 7 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But in this place no ſuch thing.</note> continu'd viſion to the 20. Chap. but,) to abandon the unbeleeving, and abominable, to the lake of fire and brimſtone, <hi>v.</hi> 8? Queſtionleſſe <hi>Joels</hi> great and terrible day of the Lord, yet attended with that incomprehenſible ſolemnity of the marriage, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the records of the Holy Prophets. How ſuitable to all this is the parable in St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. repreſenting Chriſts coming to judgment by a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>And they that were ready went in with him, &amp;c.</hi> This is that very wedding to which the <hi>Jews</hi> were bidden ſo long agoe, S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. but then like rude ſhavelings they kickt at the favour, ſo that the Gentiles were ſurrogated to the firſt part of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43449:14"/>the entertainment. For be aſſuted (dear Reader) that it enters not into my thoughts to deny theſe Nupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als to be coaetaneous with Religion; but that the<note n="[*]" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſr.</hi> muſt be admitted one day to call him <hi>Jſhi.</hi> if it were ſhe that call'd him <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li ut ſupra Hoſ.</hi> 2.16.</note> royal banquet is not yet ſerv'd in, and that the latter part of the feſtivity is the ſame with that in the <hi>Rev.</hi> there is one notable circumſtance in the context which ſtrongly evinceth, <hi>viz. a caſting forth one of the Abominable gueſts</hi> (according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.) <hi>into the Lake of darkneſs, where there is weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnaſhing of Teeth. v.</hi> 13. How facil might the way be into divers obſcurities of Scripture by the dexteritie of this Key, were it once approov'd of! I have not indeavoured to heap together what ever might be collected to this illuſtration, for truly the ſacred writings every where ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und with ſuch teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, ſo that I might quickly outſtrip my deſign of briefneſs. It ſufficeth, if the conſtant harmony of both the Teſtaments may imprint on our ſpirits this notion of the Day of judgment, <hi>viz.</hi> a conſiderable duration in which the myſtery of God declar'd to the Prophets ſhall be eſtabliſht on<note n="[a]" place="margin">Beſides what is above aſſerted, twere not amiſſe to weigh the phraſes here in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. if they can poſſibly mean otherwhere than on earth. <hi>Coming down, from God, out of Heaven. v.</hi> 2. ought it not rather to be (if ſignifying in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, going up to God, from the earth. So <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Tabernacle of God is with men, and ſhall dwell with them,</hi> not, Men are with the Tabernacle of God, and ſhall dwell with him, <hi>viz.</hi> in Heaven.</note> earth. But why ſhould we mince it all this while, and not rather ſpeak out, ſince the time is expreſly declar'd by the word, and believ'd by the firſt three Ages to be 1000. years?</p>
            <p>The Thouſand years of Satans being bound (<hi>Rev.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.2.) if they ſhould be allow'd ſtill to come, our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>terpreters are ſo ſenſible the reſult will then be that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here is a definite <hi>Millennium</hi> yet to be run over in, which our Lord is to be inveſted with ſome diſtinct manner of royaltie, that they generally bend their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43449:14"/>forces (though upon ſeveral perſwaſions) to make this ligation already paſt. The uſual dates from whence they (diverſly) reckon his binding are<note n="[a]" place="margin">The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake of them who judge the binding to be already paſt ariſeth by thinking Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans binding (Chap. 20.) the ſame with <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> conquering him Chap. 12. whereas 'tis one thing to be beaten from Heaven. <hi>i. e</hi> his ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainty in the Roman em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire which then worſhipt him in heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, another to be bound, caſt into the bottomleſſe pit, ſhut up, and ſeal'd. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inding the ſtrong man is reck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n'd in Scripture as the trophie of Chr. onely, but <hi>Michael</hi> was not Chr. as appeares <hi>Dan.</hi> 10 where Chr (<hi>viz.</hi> the man in linnen <hi>v.</hi> 5.6. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13, 14, 15.) ſpeaks of <hi>Michael</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne divers from him, See <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.21. But eſpecially the place diſtinguiſheth them <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Wo to the Inhabie. &amp;c.</hi> Whereas (Chap. 20.3.) he is ſo bound and ſeal'd as not able to deceive or hurt the nations &amp;c. He is (truly) too too much wedded to his own opinion that will not take the ſpirits comment on the action.</note> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Saviours Nativity, or his Paſſion (about what times 'tis likely ſome Oracles did ceaſe) or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or laſtly from <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> So liberal may we be to all theſe miſtakes, as to proffer them their choice, and yet uſe but one weapon to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow them all; For which ſoever of theſe be pitch'd on, the entrance of the ten-horned and the two-horned beaſts in <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. commonly expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (even by theſe accountants) of the papacy, and the ariſing of the Locuſts from the bottomleſſe pit, at the fift Trumpet, underſtood (probably) of <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediſm,</hi> muſt neceſſarily be included within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of ligation; The former as appearing in the fourth or fift century, the latter at the ſeventh. But can any reaſonable man yield that Satan (during theſe times) was, not onely bound, and ſhut up, but ſeal'd too, (mark that) that he might deceive the nations no more; while he was both looſe, and active in conveying into the world two the grandeſt impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures that ever the Chriſtian ages knew? And that his obſtetrication was aſſiſtant to both theſe births let the Spirit decide the controverſy, who (as to the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of Locuſts Chap. 9.) attributes the opening the pit to the ſtarr which fell from Heaven, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. But what I pray can this ſtarr be but Satan? and that in a double capacity, firſt as a lapſed Angell, ſecondly as lately beat down from heaven by Holy <hi>Michael,</hi> Chap. 12.7, 9. Again, Theſe Locuſts had a King,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43449:15"/>the Angel of the bottomleſſe pit, whoſe name is <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baddon, i. e.</hi> a Deſtroyer; which elogies who ever ſhall attribute to any other, he muſt begg leave either to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the bottomleſſe pit of ſomewhat els beſides Hell, or the Deſtroyer belonging to that pit of ſome one els than the Devill. Nor is our evidence leſſe cleer for his energy (farr beyond the nature of ligation and ſealing) at the nativity of the Beaſt <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. of whom it is expreſſely deliver'd <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>that the Dragon gave him power, and his ſeat, and great authority.</hi> If either of theſe inſtances may ſpeak him bound, I think the onely difficulty will be to produce a villany of ſo aggravated a malice, whereby ever to aſſert his liberty.</p>
            <p>But examine we them ſomewhat more diſtinctly. The firſt three <hi>Epochaes</hi> (yet that way takes the very learned Primate of <hi>Ireland</hi>) beſides what is already objected, implie the Devill to be bound for that whole ſpace in which Bleſſed <hi>Michael</hi> conflicted with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. Surely the bitter throwes by which Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity wrung in, and the warm blood of ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Martyrs, were arguments ſufficient to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that <hi>Michael</hi> had not to deal with a bounden Adverſary. Again. If he were then bound, the little ſeaſon of his looſing Chap. 20.3. runs on apace to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh a ſeventh centurie, and hath (Seemingly) much overſhot the proportional limits of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing farr more than half the intervall of his binding. Seriouſly, I am farr from aiming to blaſt any reverend Authorities, but doubtleſſe the Holy Jeſus requires more exact enucleations of his ſacred meſſages, than either of theſe faint reſolutions can amount to. Into ſuch intanglements are thoſe men falln who have once Slipt the clue of Truth! In a word. Can it conſiſt with Satan in a cage, and coop'd up from abuſing the world, that he ſhould be able to impoſe upon the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43449:15"/>the young Chriſtians ſo<note n="[a]" place="margin">To theſe fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agon (doubtleſs,) (and not to <hi>Garnets</hi> ſtraws,) the Ap. points in 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. [by ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, after the working of Satan] foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as, I am perſwaded) there is no opinion in which they differ from us, but (if well ſearch'd after) was either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd, or is maintain'd by ſuch colluſion.</note> rank a peece of Legerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, as by making ſhew of miraculous cures, wrought (I wiſs) by the reliques o<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Martyrs, to cheat the cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous world into the eſtabliſhment of Saint-worſhip, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the miſtaken ground (ſo groſly were they abuſed) of <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. which prerogative of the Martyrs reigning with Chriſt 1000. yeers, they expounded of this * Idolatrous Royaltie, into which the Dragon had thus gull'd them by the occaſion of thoſe wonders, which they preſum'd to be the feſtques of providence as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to point them to ſuch expoſitions. Truly if it can be prooved that Satan was all this while in his dungeon, I ſhall be the apter to think that he ſpake from his hole (through a Trunk) into <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix, at a Council in <hi>Canterbury, Anno Domini</hi> 972. (which falls within his binding, begin the account where you pleaſe,) uttering an audible voice to this purpoſe <hi>[Dunſtan's opinion is the right],</hi> he at that time being a moſt ardent Proctour againſt the allowance of Marriage to the Clergy.</p>
            <p>What ſhould now deter us from making this dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, That this very <hi>Millennium</hi> is that ſpace which the ſacred writ hath defin'd<note n="(b)" place="margin">The <hi>Millon.</hi> of ligation is confeſſedly <hi>tempus definitum.</hi> For after muſt he be looſed a little ſeaſon, <hi>Ergo</hi> that of Chriſts Kingdom is ſo too; Since one and the ſame ſpace is meant.</note> for theſe myſteries? Hear an expreſs from the Spirit, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.4. <hi>I ſaw the</hi> ** <hi>ſouls of them that were beheaded for the witneſs of</hi>
               <note n="[*]" place="margin">
                  <hi>Judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ly by theſe words of an early com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentator up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the</hi> Apoc. c. <hi>20.4.</hi> Me. ito cum Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſto &amp; vixerunt, &amp; regnarunt. Quemadmodum videmus etiam ſub fidelibus Regibus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> principibus, dum adoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur, contra omnem etiam corporis infirmita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em, ac Daemonum energiam oſtendunt dat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſibi à Deo gratiam.</note>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">If any court me over critical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtreining the Emphaſis of (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) in the Text, their partiality ought n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to make them forget with what zeal the ſame obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vation is purſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the diſpute of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">Sure this expreſſion will no way com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with their expoſition who interpret the firſt reſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he life of grace, that notion being d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeable to ſeparated ſouls, or if it were no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, yet could not the reſt of the dead, after the thouſand yeers (ſuppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d to be the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cked) ever live that life, <hi>viz.</hi> of grace. But if we give way that the ſame word [<hi>Live</hi> in the ſpace of one line, may be appliable to two ſo diffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent ſenſes, as to import the life of Grace to the one ſort, and life in its p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oper ſenſe to the other, we open ſuch a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p of licence to perverſe Cavillers, that by the opportunity of ſuch f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of acceptions they may diſtort theſe Holy Embaſſies into what ever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances may beſt ſute with their deſignes.</note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43449:16"/>
               <hi>Jeſus—And they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand yeers,</hi> which that we may reſt aſſured to be the very ſame thouſand in which the Devill is bound, the Greek affords an unavoidable evidence, for having expreſt the time of Satans binding (<hi>verſ.</hi> 2.) without an article, it delivers the ſame meaſure of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with the article as emphatically reflecting upon the foreſaid thouſand, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Where doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we ſhould not have injur'd the <hi>idiome</hi> (conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the want of (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) in the ſecond verſe,) to have Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht it <hi>thoſe thouſand years.</hi> Now ſay in good earneſt, Is it not more than likely that St. <hi>Peter</hi> intended the ſame thing, remembring, 'twas the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> paraphraſe (as you heard) of the Day of Judgment, <hi>[One day with the Lord is as a thouſand yeers]</hi> to which <hi>St. Peter</hi> (Iure) alluded? I ſhall not need to tell you of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant tradition of old <hi>Elias,</hi> (a Jew that liv'd under the ſecond Temple) to this ſenſe. 'Twere handſomer for us to remember (with ſome reverence) that the moſt inlightned, the moſt pious ages, and the moſt fruitfull of Zelous Martyrs through all the Chriſtian times, were of this minde too. And peradventure, it might do us no injury to reflect that in the thirteen following Centuries (which oppos'd it) Antichriſt both gain'd and kept his footing by the advantage of that overſight.<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Give ſentence now impartially if this Incomparable beauty of <hi>Iſrael</hi> commence not at our Lords next co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and if the commenſuration of theſe Tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies be not (in the ſacred language) <hi>the day of Judgment.</hi> What now though ſome objections may interfeer? not readily to be reſolv'd * Myſtery (my thinks) might eaſily ſtop ſuch<note n="(a)" place="margin">The <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, &amp;c.</hi> have too ſadly warn'd us that wanton wits may intangle any Truth with very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext intrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies.</note> gaping mouthes. But
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43449:16"/>for reconciling the difficulties emergent from this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, I hope hereafter (as the Lord ſhall Lend me aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and time) to appear to the World with more ample ſatisfaction; Till then give me leave ſuccinctly to propoſe a few ſuggeſtions, to abate, at leaſt, the vigour of reluctancies. If any (in the firſt place) conceit that this larger duration than they have hitherto imagin'd leads into too groſs conceptions of that divine Aſſize, as if cauſes before the Searcher of Spirits requir'd ſo ſlow a diſcuſſion, as before our earthly Tribunals; Let ſuch objectors know, that ſcruples of this kinde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed meerly from the miſtaken notion which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have fram'd of that <hi>Terrible Day;</hi> preſuming it to conſiſt one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in ſome ſhorter hearing and deciding the deeds of the World, whereas in truth (by Scripture-aſſurance) it conteines that noble chein of miracles, within which period his Judgment and righteouſneſs ſhall in an inconceivable way be manifeſted over the whole earth, and the world preſented with a Legible Comment upon that Text, <hi>[He will have mercy on whom he will have mercy]</hi> Then ſhall the<note n="(a)" place="margin">See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39 21. <hi>All the Heathen ſhall ſee my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</hi> The Prophet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (from God) about the reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t on of <hi>Jer.</hi> at the confuſion of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog.</hi> And that we may conclude it to po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th verſ. 8. <hi>This is the Day whereof I have ſpoken,</hi> where [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] (It is done) is a firm token of the final Day; as in <hi>Revel.</hi> 16, 7. at the ſeventh v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al. And <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.6. <hi>ut ſupra. de Euphraie.</hi>
               </note> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then know that he is the Lord, when he ſhall be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified before their eyes, It being his own holy names ſake (not <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s) for which he doth theſe things. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.22, 23.</p>
            <p>But time ſhall then be no longer, <hi>Revel,</hi> 10. All du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration being ſwallowed up in eternity, and no more meaſuring by Thouſand yeers. I will not here diſcuſs the Philoſophical quirk of <hi>Tempus, aevum,</hi> and <hi>aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas,</hi> though from thence (I think) was this obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hatch'd, (and this is not the firſt point in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity that hath been injur'd, by laying it too cloſe to the Philoſophy-<hi>Meet-Wand.</hi>) Nor ſhall I need to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the ſhallowneſs of that conceit, which foundeth the nature of Time on the motion of the Orbs, as if a yeer were not 52. Weeks though there were no Sun in the firmament, nor an hour the twelfth part of a day,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43449:17"/>though we knew not how to bound it by the ſhadow. To ſide-ſlip ſuch toyes as theſe, Let any one judge of this following ſenſe, if it be not cleer and round. The Lord<note n="(b)" place="margin">'Tis the Lord (who is here called the Angel that ſtood on the Sea) as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appears by his maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion verſe the firſt.</note> Chriſt ſwears (and his Oath ſure is worth the heeding) That upon the expiring of the Time, Times, and half a Time, or the 1260 Dayes, (being the limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cycle of the beaſt and his contemporals in the <hi>Revel.</hi>) there ſhall be no<note n="[a]" place="margin">Suitably to <hi>Iſ.</hi> 60.22. (ſpeaking of this myſtery) I the Lord will haſten it in his time.</note> longer time, but this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery ſhall be fulfil'd, nothing els ſhall intervene, but the ſeventh Trumpet ſhall ſound. That I have not miſcommented upon this ſacred Oath read the ſixt and ſeventh verſes together, and try if thou canſt find any other meaning. Again, examin the 5, 6, and 7. verſes of this Chapter in the <hi>Revel.</hi> by <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. and 7. The<note n="[b]" place="margin">As in the <hi>Revel.</hi> ſo in <hi>Dan.</hi> he that takes this oath is Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, being <hi>[the Man clothed in linnen]</hi> of whom ſee <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.5, 6. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.23, 14, 15.</note> perſon in both places ſtanding upon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, lifting up his hand to heaven, and ſwearing by him that liveth for ever, but in holy <hi>Daniel</hi> particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſing the Time, Times, and half a Time. Lord! that men with eyes in their heads ſhould ſtumble in ſo plain a way, and rather expound this in <hi>Daniel</hi> of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> (be their account <hi>[by Days]</hi> never ſo uneven) than allow it (in its genuine cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) to afford any light towards ſo deſpis'd a truth. One thing I am ſure of, that the countre-interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to this opinion, are forc'd, hal'd and <hi>per dures,</hi> but ſuch as run with it facil and natural, it being (without queſtion) an incomparable advantage to the extricating many Knots in the Bible, could we but once conquer that peece of pride (which we know who is ſo chid for) in eſteeming our ſelves more <hi>infallible</hi> than the firſt three hundred <hi>yeers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis often ask't how can theſe things conſiſt, ſince the notion of Judgment imports a diſtribution of Juſtice according to every ones works, allowing no capacity for converſion? ſo that if the Jews return be not till our Lord appears in the clouds, how is it that they periſh not amongſt the enemies of his Kingdom whereof they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43449:17"/>are the principal? I will return (for anſwer) the words of that admirable Divine Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> (a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man certainly of as cleer a brain as ever the world could boaſt of) <hi>I ſalve it with a ſuppoſition of ſome</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Nor will it one j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t take off from the exactreſs of the appointed <hi>Epocha</hi> (<hi>viz</hi> Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how ſhort a ſpace this miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 66.8. a place undoubtedly treating of the Jews reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>verſe</hi> 20. where alſo is ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oned the fiery expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16. <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, &amp;c. v.</hi> 22. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largment of the Gentiles. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> yea and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps This ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry latitude or</note> 
               <hi>latitude in that appearance, as being firſt to be uttered with ſome preparation or preludium to the Jewiſh Nation, before his great and univerſal appearing to the whole world to judgment. So</hi> Ceſtius Gallus <hi>the Preſident of</hi> Syria <hi>compaſſed</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>with an Army, by way of anticipation, three yeers before the final and fatal ſiege by</hi> Veſpaſian, <hi>for a warning to the believing Jews to fligh to the mountains of</hi> Arabia, <hi>according to our Saviours ſign given them</hi> Luke 21.20. <hi>For ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſuch a ſuppoſition, me thinks I diſcern in Saint</hi> Matthew (<hi>the</hi> Hebrew <hi>Evangeliſt</hi>) <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>verſe</hi> 30. <hi>two ſuch appearances intimated, The one in the words,</hi> Then ſhall appear The<note n="(bb)" place="margin">ſign of the Son of Man, <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>And I will ſend a ſign among them</hi>— conſider it.</note> ſign of the Son of man in Heaven, and all the Tribes of the earth ſhall mourn; (<hi>out of</hi> Zach. 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11, 12.) <hi>The other in the words following,</hi> And they ſhall ſee the Son of man, coming in the clouds of Heaven, with power and great glory (<hi>out of Dan.</hi> 7.)</p>
            <p>But in caſe this may not ſatisfie, ſhall we therefore dare to gainſay ſome Truths becauſe our<note n="(*)" place="margin">Myſtery, Myſtery.</note> ſhallow reaſons cannot manage them? though truly without ſome ſuch conceſſion that reverend man pleads for, I dare conclude that <hi>Malachy</hi> 4, 5, 6. will never be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood while the world ſtands. Which great and dreadfull day, <hi>that burnes like an oven, &amp;c. verſe</hi> 1. If not the day of judgment, 'twill proove but of little aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to unravell one Text by another. As for the marginal reference, pointing at <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Admit the Fathers erred concerning the perſon, and ſome other circumſtances about this <hi>Elias,</hi> yet might the ſubſtance of their opinion be true, for ſo they err'd in many part culars of the perſon, quality, and reign of Antichriſt, yet for the ſubſtance the thing was true.</note> Fathers (if we dare credit them) may deliver
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43449:18"/>us of that ſcruple, generally inclining that Chriſts his ſecond coming, (as well as his former) ſhall be uſher'd in by that celeſtial harbinger, and (probably) the ſame <hi>Elias</hi> too, <hi>viz. John the Baptiſt.</hi> If ſo, the margent breeds no repugnancy at al. It any yet had rather conſtrue this chapter of our Lords former coming, I require of him how he dares cad that the <hi>Terrible Day of the Lord, burning as an O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en, and devouring all the wicked root and branch, verſ.</hi> 1. which our Saviour himſelf calls the <hi>Accept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of the Lord, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clames general mercy to the Captives, ſight to the blind, &amp;c. Luke</hi> 4.18, 19, 21. How can that ſo ſweet a day be the ſame with this ſo dreadfull, which ſweeps a way root and branch, and allowes no quarter to the ungodly? or who will ſay that the ſpiritually<note n="(*)" place="margin">Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles phraſe <hi>[Led captive by the Devill, &amp;c.]</hi>—</note> Captiv'd, and blind, are not (during ſuch captivity) in the ſtate of wickedneſs, yet, not then confounded, but illuminated? But eſpecially how was it true of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Baptiſt</hi> in his former miniſtry (which yet Truth it ſelf ſpake of him) that <hi>Elias firſt comes and reſtoreth all things, Mark</hi> 9.12. The phraſe being the ſame with what Saint <hi>Peter</hi> uſeth, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. <hi>Reſtitution of all things;</hi> affixt to the time when he ſhall be reveal'd from heaven, <hi>verſe</hi> 21? But of that time Saint <hi>Paul</hi> will ſatisfie us, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8. that it is when he comes in flaming fire taking vengeance on them that know not God; Surely this very flaming day in <hi>Malachie, when the ungodly ſhallbe as the ſtubble, and that day as a burning Oven.</hi> Laſtly, who can poſſibly underſtand the Prophecy otherwiſe, than of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s reſtitution, it being ſo conſonant to the reſt of the Holy<note n="(*)" place="margin">See <hi>Joel Zach, &amp;c. ut ſupra. Joel</hi> 2.31. <hi>Great and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Day.</hi> Note. The glorious promiſes began to draw out in Chriſts former coming (the Kingdom, as was before advertis'd, being the ſame, though the ſtate twofold,) Whence it comes to paſs that this Prophecy of 2. <hi>Joel,</hi> is quoted in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. of thoſe dayes; to wit, The Myſtery beginning to iſſue forth then: but not to receive full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment (as to diverſe particulars) till this <hi>Terrible Day,</hi> Uſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in by the <hi>Suns darkneſs, the Moons turning into blood, &amp;c.</hi> all which, the Evangeliſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (in the receiv'd opinion of the Church) refer to the time of judgment Truly, this Note, if well obſerv'd, might cure many the like webs in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy.</note> 
               <hi>Pen-men,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:43449:18"/>who conſtantly date it on that <hi>Terrible Day?</hi> Pick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other meaning from the ſecond and third <hi>verſe,</hi> who can; Onely take in the fourth <hi>verſe,</hi> for a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor that <hi>Iſrael</hi> is here ſpoken to <hi>in propriâ per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonâ.</hi> And for a corollary, See how eaſily the ſixt <hi>verſe</hi> comes up to the ſame ſenſe. <hi>He ſhall turn</hi> (or<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo <hi>Mark</hi> 9.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ſo in <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (<hi>viz.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the <hi>Jews</hi>) may not chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominate Chriſts ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming, The time of reſtitution.</note> reſtore, ſee the LXX.) <hi>the hearts of the Fathers to the Children, and the hearts of the Children to the Fathers, i.e.</hi> He ſhall bring the refractary and unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving poſtery of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> nation, to have the ſame heart and minde their holy Fathers and Progenitors had, who feared God and beleeved his promiſes; that ſo their Fathers might as it were rejoyce in them, and own them for their own children; In plain Engliſh, he ſhall convert them to the faith of that Chriſt, whom their Fathers hoped in, and looked for. I am now much deceived, unleſs holy <hi>Gabriel</hi> interpret it the ſame way, <hi>Luke</hi> 1, 16, 17. both in ſpeaking literally of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and in paraphraſing the latter part <hi>[And The Hearts of Children to their Fathers,]</hi> by [And The diſobedient to the Wiſedom of the juſt]. Read the Bleſſed Angels comment thorow. [<hi>He ſhall go before him in the ſpirit and power of Elias, to turn</hi> (or reſtore) <hi>the hearts of the Fathers to the Children, and the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to the wiſdom of the Juſt, to make ready a people prepared for the Lord;</hi> to wit, he ſhall reduce the diſobedient off-ſpring who now kick at Chriſt, to the wiſdom and piety of the moſt zealous of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp;c. This (by the way) is moſt ſure, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in Chriſts former coming had gain'd little by this promiſe, in being effected upon them, namely <hi>[re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring the hearts of the fathers to the children,]</hi> their Anceſtry being all Pagan.</p>
            <p>As to the main difficultie of the Apocalyptical
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43449:19"/>
               <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> ſwarming, and periſhing at the end of the 1000. years, I commend every ſober Reader to the learned diſcourſe of the worthy Mr. <hi>Mead,</hi> whoſe judgment about it was exceeding ſolid, and vertuouſly modeſt, (as truly in all his tenets) and ſo powerfully convincing, that no worſe man than Dr. <hi>Twiſſe</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd his diſcovery; Be onely thus far advertis'd, that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> are very far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from thoſe in <hi>Ezek. cap.</hi> 39. the one namely, to be deſtroy'd at the beginning, the other at the end of that renowned chiliad; So hath it pleas'd his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with two fiery conqueſts to begin and end that <hi>Terrible Day.</hi> The Dawning whereof, or begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Millennium</hi> is attended with the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and the morning-judgment on the then-appearing enemies of his Kingdom; the evening, ſhut up with the univerſal reſurrection, and the final perdition of the latter <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> with the caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Satan into his everlaſting dungeon.</p>
            <p>There's none I hope will ſo diſtruſt Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as to queſtion the means of deliverance from the wrathfull flames of that day. How eaſy is it for the God we ſerve to ſend forth fire with a limited commiſſion? The guard of Angels upon the elect (<hi>Matth.</hi> 24.31.) is neither weak nor ſubject to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſight. The God of the Chriſtians can ſecure us (if he pleaſe) without ſindging in the midſt of the furnace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.27. Or peradventure the objects of that fury ſhall be ſeparated within the appointed liſts of vengeance. Who can ſay, but that Holy <hi>Joel</hi>'s valley of * <hi>Jehoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phat,</hi> Chap. 3.12. and St. <hi>John</hi>'s<note n="[*]" place="margin">Quaere, if the valley be not S. <hi>Johns</hi> Armag.</note> 
               <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageddon, Rev.</hi> 16.16. may intimate ſome ſuch thing? And why may not St. <hi>Pauls</hi> catching up in the clouds, and meeting our Saviour in the air, point at ſome miraculous reſcue from that burning oven? It may not perchance work much upon any, to hear that the <hi>Jews</hi> can produce a<note n="[*]" place="margin">
                  <hi>From</hi> Rabbi Elias.</note> tradition to this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43449:19"/>purpoſe, farr Elder than the dayes of our Saviour, though of this I am certain, that the Apoſtles in their writings alluded to divers paſſages for which there is no other Teſtimony extant in the earth ſave Jewiſh traditions. 'Twill (I dare ſay) poſe the concordance to find where the Arch-Angel diſputed with the Devill about the body of <hi>Moſes, verſ.</hi> 9. of S. <hi>Jude.</hi> And who could be angry with me if I ſhould tell him the Apoſtle ſeems to ſpeak wide enough from their ſenſe that preſume this catching up to be our immediate tranſport to heaven? He expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (me thinks) warily enough to avoyd that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, by Cloudes, and Air, leſt (poſſibly) we might imagine Heaven to be meant, whereas we meet with many other places where this caution is not ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly prompted, <hi>e. g.</hi> The fowles of heaven or of the air indifferently, for in the Hebrew notion the air is comprehended under the name of Heaven, but here (though the hebraiſm would have allow'd it) no mention of heaven, but clouds and air. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well the context 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Thoſe that ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him,</hi> not carry with him. Does not <hi>[Bring with him]</hi> imply the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſtage (after the fiery vengeance) to be the earth, not heaven? Again, <hi>Thoſe that ſleep in Jeſus,</hi> not all the dead, <hi>will God bring with him,</hi> So <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>The dead in Christ ſhall riſe firſt;</hi> What think you of the firſt and ſecond reſurrection, moſt exactly parallel to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23, 24. Of an order in the reſurrection, Chriſt the firſt fruits, afterwards, they that are Chriſt's at his coming; not all the dead at Chriſt's coming, but they that are Chriſt's; remember that;<note n="[a]" place="margin">If any one tax me for ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it [Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards] I demand why our Tranſlation turn'd the former word ſo, the two words being of the very ſame cognation and extent, the one <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the other <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ſome I perſwade my ſelf will tax them of partiality here and not me; The truth is, they obſerv'd the former had allow'd a great latitude betwixt Chriſt the firſt fruits and thoſe at his coming, <hi>viz,</hi> 1654. years (now) beſides what may be. And leſt the Millenaries ſhould catch hold on this handle, and require, Why may not the latter alſo afford the extent they plead for betwixt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, being words of equal force aad mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, (differing no way, but one made of the other) To av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id this rock, they Engliſht the firſt, Afterwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, (implying the reſpit of above 1600. years) but the ſecond, Then, as if (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) it had been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, intimating an immediate proſecution of the ſame acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereas 'Tis in the Greek not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Truly, this is ſomewhat, but I would to God this had been all the foull play Tranſlations had offer'd to this opinion. I ſhall make thee ſtart in the next Chapter, Reader.</note> Afterwards
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43449:20"/>comes the end, the univerſal reſurrection, &amp;c. How cloſe to this runs <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4.5. and who might not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veil, if the ſenſe were divers? If now univerſal tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition through the whole Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the conſtant doctrine in the firſt three centuries of Chriſtians, (acknowledg'd by the Adverſaries) foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on ſo harmonious concordance of old and new Teſtament, be not ſufficient to vindicate a truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſcoffings of fleſh and blood, objecting car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, to what is deliver'd for a Myſtery, I know not what can. <hi>The Lord open our Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Prooving (from what hath been premis'd) Chriſts perſonal reign on earth.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THat the foremention'd Beatitude is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd on earth, will (I think) ſcarcely be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by reaſonable men, for moſt certainly, the 60: Chap. of <hi>Jſ.</hi> all over, and the 65. from the 17. <hi>v.</hi> to the end (to which two, the 21. Chap. of the <hi>Rev.</hi> is in many <hi>verſes</hi> adaequate) can no way be ſatisfied but on earth, and 'tis as cleer that the reſt of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets hold an even proportion with thoſe two Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. That all this bliſſe takes riſe at the <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus's
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43449:20"/>coming to judgement in fire and vengeance,</hi> (for I deſire to be underſtood without any amphibology) I am at preſent ſtrongly perſwaded that the ſecond Chapter makes good. The onely demand that can remain is this, How for all this can Chriſts perſonal reign be aſſerted? To which I firſt retort thus, if ſuch an incomparable myſtery (to receive atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on earth) muſt enter at his next coming, how well can it be avoyded? it being m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt irrefragable that the <hi>Jews</hi> reſtauration, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> fullneſs, neither was ever, or can be imagin'd a beauty of a dayes term, but a continu'd ſtate of ſome very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable permanence; and if no more but this be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, 'twill proove a good ſtep to the Tenet, it being (I doubt not) more than ever the Adverſaries expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to find proof. But that's not all. See <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5, 6. — <hi>The Lord our righteouſneſs ſhall execute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and juſtice on the earth.</hi> If on the earth be not Engliſh, I have no more to ſay. The prophecy is<note n="[*]" place="margin">As hath been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proov'd.</note> certainly yet unfulfill'd, * <hi>vide ſupra;</hi> weigh the <hi>verſes</hi> following. Look <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.23, 24. <hi>I the Lord have ſpoken it,</hi> may help to aſſwage incredulity. See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.24, 25. To this purpoſe is <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.12. Where the Righteous branch muſt build the temple, (and in a prophecy for certain to be verified on earth <hi>v.</hi> 15.) So <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.16. where the King, the <hi>Lord of Hoſtes, is to be worſhipt at Jeruſalem.</hi> I am ſenſible enough how theſe places are commonly fruſtrated, by anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they may all be made good though Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in heaven. I yield ſo too, they might and would be true if that onely were the meaning. But then remember, that the<note n="[*]" place="margin">At the former Chap. prooves.</note> fulfilling is to be at his coming, at what time that admirable Prophecy (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt) is to be completed, <hi>Jſ.</hi> 54.5. Where <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> maker becomes her husband, in moſt admirable harmony to <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. <hi>Jſ.</hi> 62.4, 5. As alſo that other <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. The Tabernacle
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43449:21"/>of God is with men, and ſhall dwell with them, it being formerly averr'd and cleer'd, that by Tabernacle is meant the humane nature of Chriſt: I would fain be ſatisfied what other ſenſe can amount from theſe ſayings? If the humane nature's being and dwelling with men (which <hi>Ezek.</hi> alſo praedicted <hi>c.</hi> 37.) an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt in his body exerciſing righteouſneſs and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting juſtice in the<note n="[*]" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.15.</note> land, (and this in ſuch a ſtate which can not poſſibly be Momentary, to wit, the converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> &amp;c.) require not a meaning and performance in this world, we muſt deſpair of any aſſurance in expounding ſcripture. 'Tis very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable (in paſſing) that St. <hi>Paul</hi> interprets this particular prophecy of <hi>Jſ.</hi> 54. (which yet I perſwade me, will not be imagin'd accompliſhable any where than on earth, See <hi>v.</hi> 3.) to the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is above. <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.27. How think you, is not this the very ſame <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which S. <hi>John</hi> tells us (at the appointed time) comes down from God out of Heaven? Which hath been before proov'd to be the myſtery deſcrib'd by the Prophets, of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the new Teſtament, view <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>The Kingdoms of this World, &amp;c.</hi> Sure, <hi>This world</hi> is Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. For the earth, doubtleſſe, and this lower world, ſhall be the ſcene of ſome moſt eminent tranſaction, meant by Chriſts kingdom; Howbeit it was never imagin'd by any but baſe, carnal, and ignoble tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, to be leſſe than<note n="[*]" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. <hi>Jſ.</hi> 60.21: All righteous.</note> ſpiritual, and of quite another mode than the faſhion of this world; which conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alone, I am deceiv'd if it doe not fully extricate thoſe words of our bleſſed Saviour, which ſome have made uſe of for their cheif argument againſt this apprehenſion, <hi>John</hi> 18.36. <hi>My kingdom is not</hi>
               <note n="[*]" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſee <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.19. Where the knot is unti'de in S. <hi>Johns</hi> own phraſe <hi>[ye are not the World] viz.</hi> not word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> 
               <hi>of this world:</hi> 'Tis not ſaid <hi>(in)</hi> but <hi>(of) viz.</hi> not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of worldly pompe, or adminiſtration, not of the ſame notion with what fleſh and blood
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43449:21"/>ſuggeſts. or our ſhallow capacities are wont to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, briefly (as himſelf expreſſeth it) not from hence, but out of Heaven from God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. and every way a Heavenly glory, though on earth.</p>
            <p>Mean what it will, (for I never incourag'd to too much boldneſs in this myſterious abyſs) 'Tis certain we find (<hi>Rev.</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. The final glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in heaven is (ſurely) the Fathers throne, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.28. <hi>Ergo</hi> the ſons throne muſt mean ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what els. Nor yet can it be meant of his preſent Kingdom whereby he rules in our Hearts (in our mortal ſtate) being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as a ſubſequent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and not as a preſent fruition, for we are but <hi>viato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> yet; not <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores—To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh will I give, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 3.21.) a diſtinct throne appropriated to Chriſt from that which belongs to his Father. I will not multiply Texts till I have gain'd ſome footing, at what time ſome I dare ſay will wonder to ſee what (otherwiſe inextricable) problemes this clue may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intangle. Take one other, which if well underſtood ſpeaks ſo home, that it can never be avoided by any that underſtands the Greek. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Our Tranſlators (to avoid this proof) do ſtrangely tranſpoſe <hi>[Again]</hi> contrary to the order of the Greek, that it may have reference to <hi>[he ſaith,]</hi> by way of a new quotation, and not to <hi>[bringeth,]</hi> But how diſingenuouſly, let any judge. Beſides, while by ſuch a tranſpoſition they indeavour to refer the meaning of the paſſage to Chriſts former coming, do not they diametrically ſtruggle againſt <hi>St. Paul,</hi> who determineth his meaning to his next coming <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5? and that in the ſame word too, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] which all that underſtand the Greek know to ſignify moſt properly, ſtrictly and unavoidably <hi>[The Earth,]</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a participle of the feminine gender, us'd in ſingle, ſuppoſing <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be underſtood, <hi>e. g.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited Earth.</hi> Read then the Text according to the original, and judge. [<hi>And when he</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">The orig. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath the ſignification of the future tenſe, being the ſecond aoriſt of the ſubjunctive Mood, beſides, 'tis joyn'd with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Again], ſo that: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] ought (in ſtrictneſs) to be renderd <hi>[And when he ſhall bring again, &amp;c.]</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>bringeth again the firſt begotten upon the earth he ſaith, &amp;c.</hi>] But Lord! what pains ſome men will take to fool them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of truth! One thing may not be pretermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43449:22"/>that the text (as indeed the whole context) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies ſome very glorious matter, which (if S. <hi>Paul</hi> may be allow'd the Judge of his own ſenſe) is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd to<note n="(b)" place="margin">By turning it <hi>The World to come</hi> they would ſeem to mean the Kingdom of glory, but we ſhall find that the world in that ſenſe is always <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. but no where in all the Bible <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Earth to Come.</hi> What difference now between <hi>Saint Pauls</hi> ſtate of the <hi>earth to come,</hi> and <hi>S. Peters new earth?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Briefly ſhewing the uſe of this Tenet.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>BUt to what purpoſe is all this? May we not be ſav'd without the knowledge of it? Yes, I doubt not, or els, God help! But in the firſt place, 'Tis I am ſure no great bleſſing to ſtand in the number of ſuch as <hi>S. Peter</hi> brands for Scoffers, nor certainly any ſmall exemption to be deliverd from that rable. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if it were propos'd ſo many thouſand yeers agoe as a matter of ſo rich-conſolation to the hearers at that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, it aſſuredly cannot want its Treaſures of felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (if well examin'd) to us who in all likelyhood live juſt on the borders of ſo great a mutation; I am ſure much neerer than the ancient <hi>Jews.</hi> Thirdly it would take off a great ſtumbling-block, and hindrance to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, from the poor miſtaken <hi>Jew,</hi> who (being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with ſo univerſal tradition of Anceſtry) upon this ſtock, both hates and ſcorns us; And count we it a ſmall thing to be inſtrumental in ſo great a work towards <hi>Iſrael?</hi> for whom the Deareſt Jeſus hath<note n="*" place="margin">See the 137. <hi>Pſal.</hi> and the 13. and 14. ch. of <hi>Iſ.</hi> all over.</note> yet ſo yerning bowells that he will <hi>bleſs them that bleſs her? Numb.</hi> 24.9. What though the plenteous vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their return be not expected till our Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet think we not that ſome few cluſters of grapes would be an acceptable offering unto our Lord? How
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43449:22"/>ardently might it affect the deſpiſed <hi>Hebrew</hi> to ſpie the gracefull portray of his hopes in our New Teſtament? How could his heart perſiſt ſo irrationally obſtinate, as not ſtraitway to yield our Jeſus to be their Meſſiah, did but our Commentators dandle their rugged ſoules by the gentle parallels of our Teſtament with theirs, and Kindly point from <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.7. to <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10? By which feſtque they might ſoon diſcern that this is He, whom they once ſo barbarouſly pierc'd, and for whom (at<note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Jews</hi> to this day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not the Meſſiah be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of Judgment. <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
               </note> his next coming) they ſhall mourn with ſo deep compunction. But while they obſerve us to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtort the Scriptures (in avoidance of this opinion) by rough and unnatural expoſitions, ingroſſing all to<note n="*" place="margin">By our Gloſs of Goſpel-times, &amp;c. <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
               </note> our ſelves, and defrauding their expectations of ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, in which I dare ſay they have the better half: they are ſcandaliz'd at our partiality, deride our gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, and grow confirm'd in their infidelity. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it were the way to avoid almoſt every hereſy that now reigns, ſince there can ſcarce one be nam'd, which hath not been built upon the miſtaken grounds of this opinion. Thus <hi>Vavaſor Powel</hi> Imps his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon this ſtock, counting the Kingdom of the Saints to be erected in his tribe. The Anabaptiſts in <hi>Germany</hi> (and the Levellers, their offſpring, here,) pleaded that they were the Saints that muſt inherit the earth. Nay, it is wonderfull, that Popery, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>e. g.</hi> The Quakers, ſo numerous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us.</note> abominations crept in by the overſight of this tenet. Laſtly, It opens an eaſy poſſibility for the interpretation of many knotty perplexities in Scripture, about which the weakneſs of ſome, the countreſtrifes of many, and the uncertainty of all, make our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators ridiculous, and our Religon ſubject to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. I could name divers, (and hope to do ſo in an after-treatiſe) But now I aim at briefneſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:43449:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Shewing, that by miſunderſtanding this opinion, the Jewes miſtook Chriſt, and the Gentils let in Antichriſt.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THat the Meſſiah was expected by the <hi>Jews</hi> in the age our Saviour was born, is ſo cleer, that it needs no proof, <hi>Daniels</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 9.24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>WEEKS</hi> had ſo daded them to the very time; From hence aroſe their ſwelling hopes that <hi>the Kingdom of God ſhould immediatly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, S. Luke</hi> 19.11. Which apprehenſion, to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as underſtood it<note n="(a)" place="margin">'Tis always the ſame King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, though under a two-fold ſtate as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſhewed from <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. &amp;c.</note> rightly, the Holy Spirit never taxeth, but backs it with a gracious elogie, <hi>S. Mark</hi> 15.43. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.51. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.25.37.38. But ahlas! the traditions of the Elders had interlac'd it with ſo many<note n="(b)" place="margin">About that time All the Eaſt (as <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> informs us) expected a King to rule over the whole world.</note> ſecular appertenancies, and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pageantryes, that the ſubtil Dragon by this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage dazzeld their fancyes with the glaring ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of their miſtaken, and falſly pitched pomp, whereby the eyes of that unhappy age, now (God wot,) made dim by ſuch ſpangling flaſhes, quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lookt the meaner obſcuritie of his former coming, through their ill-manag'd conceptions of that miſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented glory. Upon this miſtake they proceeded, (<hi>John</hi> 6.) being convinc'd by the miraculous enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, that he was that Prophet in whom theſe glorious promiſes (miſinterpreted by them) were to find accompliſhment, to make him a King. <hi>verſe</hi> 14, 15. Thus in a word they overſaw that<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 22.16.</note> morning-ſtar, becauſe their abuſed minds had not learnt to look for him in that duskie cloud of his firſt appearance, nor rightly to diſtinguiſh of his two-fold coming, whereas the paſſages for both, through the whole Scriptures, were ſo cleer and pregnant, that it had been impoſſible
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43449:23"/>for any Sophiſter below the Devill to have fruſtrated their perſpicuity; nor he (I think) by any weaker ſhade than the power of darkneſs.</p>
            <p>'Twas a feat of the ſame hand that juggl'd Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt into the world; for this moſt lovely beauty within ſome while contracted ſo much ſoyl (through the odious defilements of unworthy minds) that by zealous <hi>Euſebius</hi>'s dayes many conſcientious profeſſors choſe rather to gainſay the authority of the<note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. was one of thoſe zelotical An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichiliaſts, and did his beſt to undermine the <hi>Rev.</hi> o ſtrange!</note> 
               <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps</hi> it ſelf, than afford enterteinment to what they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd ſo ridiculous a vanity. The Devill could wiſh for no greater averſeneſs than to become ſo ſhie, as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deny Scripture than embrace a truth! About thoſe times the accurſed <hi>Julian</hi> muſt needs inquire of <hi>Apollo</hi>'s <hi>Oracle</hi> concerning his Perſian War, where the cunning Devill turns ſullen, and would not be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd by his many Sacrifices to the favour of an anſwer, At laſt his Coyneſs (being ſollicited Why ſo mute) was courted forſooth into this ſly return, that the corps (I wis) of <hi>Babylas</hi> the Martyr (buried neer his temple in <hi>Daphne</hi>) ſtopped his wind-pipe. <hi>Babylas</hi> is forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with (at the Emperours appointment) diſlodg'd by the Chriſtians, (when without doubt reliques of ſo apparent an efficacy were covetouſly ſnatch'd at by the remoovers) ſo that a conceit was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſprung, that other Martyrs bones might be found upon triall as terrible to the Devill as thoſe of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylas,</hi> which was no ſooner eſſayd, but expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience preſently verifi'd it with improvement, and all the world ſo rung with wonders done by Martyrs, that even holy men were at length ſurpriſed, and carried away with the power of deluſion; No more need now of queſtioning the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Wonder not Reader, that the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of this truth, ſhould anciently challenge the <hi>Revel.</hi> for this Myſterie is ſo cloſely interwoven with that ſac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Book; that it is impoſſible for rational and impartial men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein the one and reject the other. See <hi>Revel.</hi> 10.7. <hi>chap.</hi> 11.15. <hi>chap.</hi> 20.4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 21. all over, paralleld with Prop. &amp;c.</note> Revelation; Nay, but ſhake
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43449:24"/>hands and be friends rather, for Heaven hath reſolv'd the controverſie—Thus divers ran a gadding after the Dragons lure, and ſhortly fell to ſuch expoſitions of <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.4. (about the Martyrs reigne) as might ſeem to eſtabliſh Saint-worſhip <hi>cum privilegio,</hi> and authorize ſuch<note n="(b)" place="margin">The main and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental error of Antichriſt, is ſpiritual fornication, or plurality of objects in divine worſhip, for this cauſe is it ſaid, <hi>The Whore of Babylon,</hi> not, the Lyar, Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dreſs, or Tyrant of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon; ſo that the riſte of Saint-worſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p is certa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly the Epocha of Antichriſt. But thou wilt marvail Reader how th s abomination ſurpriz'd (in a manner) the whole Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an world ſhortly after the time of <hi>Julian,</hi> this cheat (no doubt) prooving an unimaginable ſnare to the inadvertent Chriſtians.</note> invocations upon the avouchment of providence it ſelf, <hi>v. ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Humbly preſenting to all Chriſtian minds certain characters from the ſacred Bible, which ſeem to denote that This Dreadfull Day, which ſhall burn like an oven, is hard by upon us.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the firſt place it is moſt certain that there is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited time, cleerly expreſt in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> upon the expiring whereof hath paſt an oath from<note n="(c)" place="margin">That it is the Lord that ſwears, and this the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of time, upon which the Oath is pitch'd, See a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, from Holy <hi>Dan. cap.</hi> 12.7. Where is plainly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd (in the Oath) Time, Times, and half a Time. Beſides, 'tis the bound of Antichriſt, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Beaſt, <hi>cap.</hi> 13.5.) whoſe deſtruction we know to be at the day of Judgment. 2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 2.8. <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt himſelf, that time ſhall be no longer, <hi>Revel.</hi> 10.6. This limit is declar'd to be 42. months, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.5. or 1260. dayes, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.3. <hi>chap.</hi> 12.6. or a <hi>Time, Times</hi> and half a <hi>time, ch.</hi> 12.14. being all but the various expreſſions of the ſame Meaſure (<hi>viz.</hi> of the Beaſt, and his coaetaneans,) So many dayes making exactly 42. months, and thoſe months amounting juſtly to <hi>Time, times,</hi> and an <hi>half,</hi> to wit, three yeers and a half. If now the spirit hath alſo determin'd whether
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43449:24"/>this period be meant literally for 3. ſingle yeers and a half, and manifeſtly propounded where the account ſhall begin, we can not ſure be ſo irrational but to conclude this to be an incomparable act of favour in our Lord (to afford his Church ſo ſweet a<note n="(a)" place="margin">Thus was he pleas'd to deal with his people concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his firſt coming, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24, 25. as alſo about the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Jeruſalem, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.20. being two paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of as high concernment as could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to the Church.</note> warning, and incouragement to vigi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ancy) and a moſt rude ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect in our ſelves if we deſpiſe ſo great ſalvation: But (really) both theſe doubts are explain'd, (and therefore Reader, truſt our Bleſſed Jeſus on his Word, for the Apocalyps, (as thou ſhalt ſee ere I conclude) unties all the objections to the contrary.) The former, about the underſtanding of the Dayes, is apparently diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verd to be<note n="(b)" place="margin">They muſt needs imply ſome defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive time, the Scripture uſing no num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but thoſe which the uſe of ſpeech hath made ſuch, as, 1.10.1000. But mixt and comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und numbers as theſe are, 3½.42.1260. are neither in the Hebrew, nor (perhaps) in any other Language uſed indefinite y. If then a definite limit be here implyed, it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt needs be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hiſtorical or Prophetical. Nay, that thou mayſt be confident that Day is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken here fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Yeer, I may chance hereafter to advert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe thee of a moſt wondrous p ediction, once given out upon this very ground in the <hi>Rev.</hi> which proved ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to the very day.</note> Prophetical, (namely Dayes for Yeers) <hi>cap.</hi> 11. It being the ſpace of the Witneſſes prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſackcloth, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. who muſt lie dead three dayes and a half, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. and after that flouriſh again, <hi>verſe</hi> 11. Now if the three days and a half of their lying dead cannot poſſibly be underſtood hiſtorically, [for three ſingle days] (for how can the Inhabitants of one ſide of the earth ſend gratulatory Meſſages to the other, by way of inſulting over the dead Prophets, in three bare dayes and a half? <hi>verſe</hi> 10.) No more can the 1260. dayes of their mourning: for as much as they are all parts of the ſame ſtory, and muſt neceſſarily be taken in the ſame ſenſe. <hi>Ergo, Day</hi> for <hi>Yeer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The latter, of the <hi>Ep cha</hi> from whence the Lord will have this number reckond ſeemes full as evident, <hi>ch.</hi> 12. The womans a bode in the Wiſderneſs (whither ſhe fled from the Dragon) is but theſe 1260. dayes <hi>v.</hi> 6.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43449:25"/>If then it be reveal'd, when firſt ſhe flew thither, the intent of ſuch a mercy was (aſſuredly) for his people to reckon from; Come now and ſee the goodneſs of our God <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. And WHEN the Dragon ſaw that he was caſt unto the earth, He perſecuted the woman-And to the woman were given two wings of a great Eagle that ſhe might fligh into the wilderneſs; Tell me, is not here a plain [WHEN] from which thou ought'ſt to count? Doth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight of Hiſtory cleer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y make appear when the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gon was finally caſt down, that is, when heatheniſm receiv'd ſo remarkab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a blow, that it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after that made head any more in the Roman Empire? a moment ſo eminent that after it their never ſucceeded a Pagan<note n="(a)" place="margin">The Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon was caſt down from Heaven, <hi>verſe</hi> 8. <hi>i. e.</hi> from the ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and top of dominion, which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyd during the time the Emperours were heathens, &amp;c.</note> Emperor?<note n="(b)" place="margin">This muſt needs be the genuine expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning the Dragon, for if <hi>Michael</hi> be the champion of the Church, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. The Dragon (that fights againſt him) muſt needs be the Chieftain of Heatheniſm.</note> 
               <hi>Ethniciſm</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after publickly maintain'd, nor any open attempt ever made for reſtoring it again? If all this be legible (in great letters) to as many as will take the pains to look into Eccleſiaſtical ſtory, wilt thou ſtill perſiſt in doubtfulneſs about what time the Dragon was thrown down? Nay, has providence ſo ſtrengthned our aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, by a collateral confirmation, that<note n="(c)" place="margin">The very words of the Hiſtorian run thus, <hi>Theodoſ.</hi> contracted his ſickneſs ſoon after his return from the battail againſt <hi>Eugenius,</hi> and dyed, &amp;c.</note> ſcarce was this noble victory accompliſht, but the great Eagle was manifeſtly diſplayd in her two wings by which the Woman fled, and muſt all this paſſe for caſualtie? for the very next yeer, good <hi>Theodoſius</hi> (under whom this renowned battle was fought) was call'd for by our Lord, of whom the Hiſtorians (never dreaming, in that, I dare ſay, of the <hi>Apocalyps</hi>) make this expreſs, and ſignal animadverſion, that He remarkably by his Teſtament divided the Empire (the enſigne whereof was the Eagle, as every School-boy hath heard) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his two ſons <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Honorius,</hi> aſſigning to one the Empire of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> to the other of the <hi>Weſt;</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:43449:25"/>Say Reader, were not here given the two wings<note n="*" place="margin">From this time of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire between two <hi>Caeſars, Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> it conſtantly remain'd ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded, to the very ruine of the Empire, whereas the Div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſion by <hi>Conſtantin</hi> was quickly made up again; And 'tis remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable that <hi>Conſtantin</hi> left it to three ſons, but <hi>Theod.</hi> to two only; two Wings, &amp;c.</note> of the great Eagle? Conſider it. But I will relate thee the ſtory more diſtinctly, with the very obſervable cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances attending it, in the very words (for the moſt part) of ſober and godly Mr. <hi>Simſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the year 394. <hi>Eugenius</hi> (that fierce Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion for the Dragon, and one that threatned to be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Julian</hi>) came with his Chieftain <hi>Arbogaſtus,</hi> at the head of an exceeding formidable Army againſt <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the great, upon the bate quarrell of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the very deſign of reſtoring Ethniciſm, brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the two Armies ingage, <hi>The battail went hardly with the Chriſtians at the beginning, but</hi> Theodoſius <hi>had his recourſe to God by prayer, and the Lord ſent a mighty tempeſt of</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">O Nimium dilecte Deo! cui fundit ab an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris Aeolus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matas hyemes, cui malitat aether, Et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurati veniunt ad claſſica ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. <hi>Claudian. of this mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>winde, which blew ſo vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the face of</hi> Eugenius <hi>his Army, that their darts were turned back by the violence of the wind in their own faces. The Tyrant</hi> Eugenius <hi>fell down at the feet of</hi> Theodoſius <hi>to beg pardon, but the Souldiers purſu'a him ſo ſtraitly, that they ſlew him at the Emperours feet.</hi> Arbogaſtus <hi>fled, and, being out of all hope of ſafety, ſlew himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How thinkſt thou (Reader)? Is it altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable that this ſhould be the date of the Dragons downfall? Could providence have us'd a more oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune feſtque, to point at a conqueſt over the Devill, than by the ſuggeſtion of a tempeſt? Whereby the Prince of the Air might ſeem vanquiſh'd in his own dominions, and by his own weapon too <hi>(a tempeſt.)</hi> Where ſhould Angells skirmiſh (<hi>Revel.</hi> 12.7.) but in the Air? And if <hi>St. John</hi>'s words [<note n="(b)" place="margin">Howbeit, <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Text may ſeem to imply ſome ſuch manner of conflictati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt Angels, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the managing of ſublunary affaires. <hi>Dan</hi> 10.20. This will all grant, that the works of divine providence, and government, are executed by Angels.</note> 
               <hi>War in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi>] may chance not to intimate ſome ſuch thing, (though in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> notion the Air (as I ſaid) is comprehended under the name of Heaven,) yet what hinders but we may be prompted to make reflections
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43449:26"/>upon them by ſo tranſcendent (and ſignificant) a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance as this of a tempeſt? Beſides, may not the conſideration of <hi>Theodoſius</hi>'s praying hint ſome ſuch divine matter to thee? Thou ha'ſt heard, I dare ſwear, (I would thou had'ſt alwayes rememberd as well) that t'as been a rul'd caſe in the Church, time out of mind, <hi>Preces &amp; Lachrymae, &amp;c.</hi> No other weapons are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd us (in the conteſt of Religion) but thoſe; while <hi>Theodoſius</hi> contended by armes, the Devill was too hard for him, the Chriſtians were ſore put to't. 'Twas not the proper artillery for Religion. But ſo ſoon as the hand drops the ſword, and is lifted up, Holy <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi>'s partie carryes it cleer? No ſooner is this <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Ammunition</hi> recurr'd to, (Prayer's a Winged Weapon) but the Adverſary's darts recoyl upon his own pate, and the Dragon maul'd by a tempeſt. If this therefore ſhould be the paſſage at which the B. Spirit here aimes, (and prayer ſpeaks as fair for <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael,</hi> as the tempeſt pointingly to the Dragon,) then I am ſure can it not be farr to our journies end (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) thou canſt not but take notice of ſome admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable exactneſs (mean what it will) that about the ſame pitch of time the Empire ſhould be divided too; <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> (leſt too wide a latitude might render the reſt doubtfull) ſickning and dying<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>viz.</hi> About the beginning of <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 395. to which if we ad 1260, it guides down to about 1655. I determin nothing, but barely preſent it thee Reader as the duty of my charity, Though other mens principles (as well as theſe) have leveld at 55 or 56, or ſome time thereabouts. The Judge (for certain) is at the doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The Lord make us watchfull. Though I am no great favourer of Modern Revelations, yet I cannot but account it the offering of my Charity to advertiſe thee of that memorable paſſage of Mr. <hi>William Sedgwick,</hi> being a Miniſter of ſober and very conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious account, who <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1646. at his devotions, receiv'd a voice (with an appearance) to this ſenſe, Go, tell thy fellow-brethren that yet ten days and the Day of the Lord ſhall be. 'Tis well known, he was faithfull to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and miſunderſtanding the import of the <hi>Time</hi> imagin'd it to ſignifie ten natural days. But he was not the firſt that might receive divine meſſages and not underſtand them. I heard (ſaith <hi>Daniel</hi>) but I underſtood not. <hi>chap.</hi> 12.8. This I am certain: He was carried on with ſo extraordinary a power, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding grave, rational, and Holy men can bear witneſs for him, how in moſt places he came, he overthrew all the ſtrong holds to the contrary. <hi>London</hi> and that part of the Kingdom know him by the moe-name of <hi>Dooms-day-Sedgwick.</hi> But conſider it Reader, for it ſuits very marvailouſly with the period of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyps. And remember our Chronologers compute the diſtance from the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> to the flood about the ſame ſpace that the Revelation ſeems to allow from the ſecond to <hi>Adam</hi> the fire.</note> ſhortly after his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43449:26"/>return from this battail, ſay's Mr. <hi>Symſon,</hi> who, (I dare cleer the man) never thought of the Apocalyps in ſpeaking it. This ſacred Book affords many other mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailous characters of the ſame importance, all concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in the foreſaid date of <hi>Theodoſius</hi>'s death; as, the firſt Trumpet, the ariſing of the Beaſt out of the Sea, (applyable to <hi>Alaricus</hi>'s ſtormy invaſion that very yeer) The firſt trampling the outer Court by Gentili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Chriſtians, (for ſeriouſly popery is no better than Chriſtned-Paganiſm) and the appearance of the two horned falſ Prophet, for the emergency whereof about this very time you would wonder to hear what might be produc'd, but my deſign at preſent allowes it not, but hereafter may. I will therefore ſhut up all with theſe following <hi>Quaeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7. might not be intended by our gracious Lord for a ſign to his Church of the 1260. dayes of their mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, (<hi>verſe</hi> 3.) and the contemporals, to be then drawing to an end, when we ſhould ſee that more than ordinary contempt, and deſolation upon the Prophets? and for this regard chiefly (not ſo much (happily) for the grievouſneſs) might it obtein a ſingular remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and deſcription,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture if this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> weeks be well obſerv'd, it may ſeem to be the method of our Lords gracious dealing with his ſervants to be ſo indulgent to their frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties a to allow them predictive warnings of his ſuture intendments, to ſerve as ſweet incitements to their watchfulneſs, and incouraging-advantages to their diligence.</note> even as the invironing of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the Army of <hi>Ceſtius Gallus,</hi> about three yeers before the fatal ſiege by <hi>Titus,</hi> was foretold by our Saviour as a warning, that the deſolation thereof drew neer, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.20.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:43449:27"/>
            <p> Secondly, Whether this preſent calamity, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable conculcation of Proteſtantiſm, (for that, (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the miniſtry,) muſt needs be the atteſtation of Gods truth, if the Papacy be the beaſt,) Sound not as a comment on <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.7. conſidering how viſible it is to every eye, that the beaſt which aſcends from the bottomleſs pit, (<hi>i. e.</hi> the ſame beaſt we are wont to expound Antichriſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.8.) is the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and actor of our ruin, as appears by his Legion of Jeſuits and other emiſſaries ſwarming amongſt us, transforming themſelves often into illiterate (but<note n="(aa)" place="margin">Inquire (Reader) of what is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond-Sea-Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naries, that the Students are accuſtom'd (for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation at luſory houres) to addict themſelves to ſome manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture or other, whereby they become profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in literal, but mechanick knowledge too; what ever thou thinkſt on't, truly it ſeemes no leſs to me than a head-form po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of the Dragon; for by this opportunity they iſſue out among the reformed Churches, ſome for g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fted Shoomakers, others, for inſpir'd Weavers, &amp;c. to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of our Reformation.</note> gifted) <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> otherwhile into deſperate <hi>Arians,</hi> yea and ſometimes (doubtleſs) into <hi>Anabaptiſts, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and Converted <hi>Jews</hi> (as that late famous Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor at <hi>Hull,</hi>) ſtriking by all means poſſible at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry root and life of our Religion, everting (to their power) the principles of our holy faith, diſtracting us into infinity of ſchiſmes, and varieties of opinion; and (upon all oportunities) inſulting over our weaker <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techumeni;</hi> Where's now your Proteſtant Church? Can there any ſix of your Miniſters be produc'd that conſent (univerſally) in one belief? nay can ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any miniſters at all? Have not your ſelves confeſt, (and often ſtruggled in the Controverſie)<note n="(b)" place="margin">What ever excuſe may be found in this matter for other Reformed Churches (who are wont to plead neceſſity) can no way (as I ſee) relieve the Presbyterians of England, where Epiſcopacy, was wilfully, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confiderately, abominably, (and well if not ſacrilegiouſly) rejected by them.</note> 
               <hi>No Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, no Miniſtery,</hi> Epiſcopacy being the known and onely Door through all ages by which miniſters were initiated into their function, &amp;c. In plain termes this laſt blow ſtabs us to the heart, the truth being a gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one, and made good by thoſe two admirable Lights <hi>D. Hammond</hi> and <hi>D. Taylor,</hi> againſt all the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians in Chriſtendom. Judge now whether the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant-Prophets
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43449:27"/>be not<note n="(c)" place="margin">Miſtake not all the time in which the Prophets lay with dying pangs upon them (for that's far more than three dayes ½) for that for which they lye dead, But happily I may hereafter acquaint thee with ſuch a moment of their fatal blow, (after which there appear'd no more hope for them in the world) that may ſeem very probable to thee; From that time might'ſt thou call them ſtark dead, all hopes being then cut off; whereas while any hope laſted thou could'ſt not ſay were Dead.</note> dead, which cannot (at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) propagate their likeneſs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, would it not be conſider'd whether the ſundry preſſing importunements to read this Book (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing far more than to any book in the Bible) may not import that the contents of this letter do after ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar manner concern the ſons of men, in reſpect of thoſe advantaging diſcoveries, and moſt indulgent communications of our maſters pleaſure, through all the ages of the Church? the Chriſtian and pious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation whereof may fortifie our reſolutions againſt all the black accidents we meet with in our pilgrimage; (being no other than what our Lord hath given us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to expect in their appointed ſeries;) and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſolicit us to a prudent watchfulneſs, and hold us to our continual guard (againſt any poſſible ſurprizall in our times) down to the great and dreadful appearance of our Deareſt Lord. Examin this thing well (as thou lov'ſt thy ſoul) Good Reader, and try if it be a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of my own. See, if the proeme to this ſacred peece imply not what I ſpeak. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this Prophecy, and keep thoſe things that are written therein, for</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>q. d.</hi> From this time henceforth the Words of this Prophecy declare the rank of events in their order, therefore, <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the time is at hand.</hi> How often is inculcated (in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third Chapters) that memorable <hi>Epiphonema? [He that hath an ear to hear let him hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches]</hi> even ſeven times, (the number of the Churches, all concern'd in it) at the end of each Epiſtle. What leſs can'ſt thou make of <hi>Revel.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Come up hither, and I will ſhew thee the things
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43449:28"/>which ſhall be hereafter?</hi> That ſure muſt needs be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſtruſtfull Soul which accounts not this invitation to extend farther than barely to S. <hi>John.</hi> Or, ſuppoſe, no farther, yet was not all Scripture given for inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Such winning compeliations we find from the mouth every of the four proclaming<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> creatures (<hi>chap.</hi> 6.)<note n="**" place="margin">Our ſweet Saviours own inviting lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage <hi>John</hi> 1.39.</note> 
               <hi>Come and ſee;</hi> And that none may at any time think himſelf unconcern'd, look <hi>Revol.</hi> 13.9. <hi>If any man have an ear to hear let him hear.</hi> After all this, begin to think with thy ſelf, whether it may not be one of the<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quaere</hi> it be not the Devils me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to caſt ſome veil of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice upon ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein the moſt advantagious diſcoveries to the Church? The place is now well known (thanks to that Oracle Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> no other man, I think, ever diſcerning it) <hi>viz. Iſ.</hi> 9.1.2. by muddying whereof, he ſtruck the chief ſtroke to the Jewes overſeeing the Meſſiah, which had they cleerly underſtood, it had led them down moſt infallibly to expect his chiefeſt converſation and miniſtery in <hi>Galilee.</hi> Whereas their want of intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in this paſſage of <hi>Iſ.</hi> turn'd it into their chiefeſt ſnare, wanting (as they miſpreſum'd) divine warrant for his abode there, ſo that it became their ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-block, Doth any Prophet ariſe out of <hi>Galilee?</hi> Nay, and that to good <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel</hi> himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 1.46. Doth any good thing come out of <hi>Nazareth?</hi> being a City of <hi>Galilee.</hi> For ſo groſs a miſt had the Deceiver thrown on that Text (and conſequently ſo aliene an interpretation) that <hi>S. Matth.</hi> being carried by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit to refer (for this purpoſe) to that place, was fain to leave out the Devils trumpery with which the Septuagint was choak'd in the Evangeliſts dayes, and ſo ſtill remains; compare, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.15. with <hi>Iſ.</hi> 9.1.</note> Devills principal ſtratagems, to deterr the Chriſtians (as we uſually ſee) from venturing on this book, and to repreſent it as a ſort of high preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo much as to take a Text from it, being dreſt all over in riddles. 'Tis true indeed our Lord is pleas'd to ſpeak there in prophetical Schemes and Allegories, which ('tis probable) were once no leſs familiar and uſual to the Nations of the Orient, than our Poetical Schemes and Pictures are to us at this day. This is moſt certain, that a wary obſerving the Prophetical language, and emblematical manner of ſpeakings in the Old Teſtament, is a moſt unconceivable advantage to the dilucidation of theſe viſions, whereby it may ſeem that ſuch types as thoſe were Anciently very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and of eaſy apprehenſion to the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Such Symbolical ſpeech we find in <hi>Indian, Azyptian,</hi> and <hi>Perſian</hi> monuments ſtill extant among us.</note> Eaſtern
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43449:28"/>Countryes; Nay, who can ſay but the primitive times had Apoſtolical expoſitions (commended to choicer hands) to untie the more reſerv'd perplexities of Scripture? One thing I can tell thee, that many wiſe men have conceiv'd Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s words to <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 14. <hi>verſe,</hi> of the good <hi>depoſitum</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, to imply ſome ſuch matter. Then tell me ſeriouſly, ſhall we therefore neglect our Lords moſt deer and ſweet letter (and one of ſo much admirable and uſeful importance to our ſelves) becauſe he hath veild it with ſuch a dialect as may prove an inſtigation to our induſtry? And why wilt thou ſo wrong our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter as to intitle upon him a meſſage of his commands to us, which yet can no poſſible way be in our times underſtood; eſpecially after ſo familiar a key as he hath been pleas'd to afford us (<hi>Revel.</hi> 17) by which if well regarded, and us'd to the beſt advantage, we may (in a good meaſure) open the reſt of the ſecret? Which Ch. whoever ſhall anſwer to be alſo allegorical, muſt give me leave to tell him that he appeares little better than a mad man (if not a blaſphemer of our Lord) who will venture to ſay, when the Angel undertakes the part of an interpreter, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. that ſuch words alſo are Enigmatical. <hi>If to tell the myſtery,</hi> be not to ſpeak in plain termes, and make a darker matter cleer, we muſt never expect to underſtand <hi>Engliſh</hi> while we breath. Again, what poſſible uſe could there be of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine outcry, <hi>Revel,</hi> 18.4. <hi>Come out of her (i. e. Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon) O my people,</hi> (which yet none can deny to be an infinit favour) if it could in no wiſe be learnt where that <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould be? O therefore take we heed (Deer Reader) leſt we injure the ſweet ingenuity of the Lamb who was ſlayn, and hath open'd that ſealed Book for our ſake, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.9.<note n="[a]" place="margin">If open, then ſure to be read.</note> who therefore holds it forth to us, no longer in a ſealed, but an<note n="*" place="margin">'Tis Chriſt that holds the Book, being the Angell on the Sea, &amp;c. <hi>ut ſupra ex Dan.</hi>
               </note> open form, <hi>Revel.</hi> 10.8. and ſends forth ſtrait charge that thenceforth it ſhould be ſeal'd no more, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.10.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43449:29"/>yea, and at the drawing up quickens our regard towards it, with the ſame motive he had us'd in the beginning; <hi>Bleſſed is he that keeps the ſayings of this Book, Rev.</hi> 22.7. As before, <hi>Bleſſed is he that reads, &amp;c.</hi> But who can be bleſſed in reading, or who can poſſibly keep what he cannot underſtand? Reading without under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding was never any way to bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But of that Day and hour knoweth no man, no not the Angels, neither the Son, but the Father, Mark.</hi> 13.32. I deſire to ſeem no otherwiſe than ſceptical in all theſe difficulties. But I pray confer with <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. Where our Bleſſed Lord opens the ſealed Book, and the worthineſs to open it, is attributed to his being ſlain, <hi>[Thou art worthy, &amp;c. for thou waſt ſlain.]</hi> The Son himſelf (as man) before his Paſſion (we may ſpeak't with a holy Reverence) had not this myſtery revealed to him; 'Twas onely (as yet) in the Fathers hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.7. The Son at thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time unſlain, unglorified. The Book was as yet a ſealed one (anſwerable to <hi>Da.</hi> 12.4.9.) But the Captain of our ſalvation (who was made perfect through ſufferings, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9, 10.) hath now both unſeal'd it, and Commanded it for ever to abide ſo, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.10. So that may we not now think (as the Apoſtle ſeemes to intimate, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.4. &amp; 5.) that if that Day doe overtake any as a Theef in the night, (though this alſo uſeth to be another objection) they'r only ſuch as are in darkneſs, and not the Children of the Light? 'Twill (indeed) appear as the flood in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> finding men eating, drinking, &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.37. But neither doth that Text implie the want of all light in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oracles whereby we may be guided into this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, but rather the hardneſs of mens hearts, as it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah;</hi> when (ſure) his ſo long continuance in the building an Ark might have been conviction ſufficient to any (but men before drown'd in ſecurity) that the Flood was coming. Might not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43449:29"/>every ſtroke upon that ſignal Fabrick have proov'd a Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mon of repentance to ingenuous minds? Conſult with that place of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſee if upon this very ſcore it call not holy <hi>Noah</hi> the Preacher of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. To which purpoſe alſo may that other more obſcure paſſage of the ſame Apoſtle be urg'd far more ſenſibly (I trow) than it is wont to ſerve for Purgatory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19, 20. Namely that Chriſt by his Spirit preacht (in the Miniſt'ry of <hi>Noah,</hi>) to thoſe rebellious miſcreants, of ſo narrow and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd Spirits, that they allow'd not themſelves ſo much liberty of reaſon, and freedom of diſcourſe, as to collect that the threaten'd Flood muſt needs be approaching, though they ſaw an Ark ſo long in rearing. Anſwer me (Reader) doth not [the long ſuffering of God, waiting in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> while the Ark was preparin] mention'd by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> produce this reſult, That they in the days of <hi>Noah</hi> obtain'd a very mercifull premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.3. Yet his days ſhalbe an hundred &amp; twenty years, being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (nay, and by our Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node-Notes too) of Gods prediction concerning the Deluge.</note> in which they might have read the intentions of his vengeance upon thoſe times, had not their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate reluctancies rendred thoſe ſweet opportunities ineffectual to themſelves? And if the State of the World at his ſecond coming be as it was then, (as ſo we hear it muſt) doth it not imply the Indulgence of our Lord in gracious forewarnings, but our own defective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their obſervation?</p>
            <p>Who ever (after all this) ſhall think this ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time a needleſs curioſity, let him remember how our Saviour reproov'd the Jewes for neglect hereof, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.56. <hi>O yee Hypocrites, yee can diſcern the face of the skie, but how is it that yee do not diſcern this time? viz.</hi> that this is the very age in which the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah is to be born. And that this was our Holy Saviour's meaning appears by that other famous paſſage of his recorded by the ſame St. <hi>Luke ch.</hi> 4. Where our deereſt Jeſus in meer deſign to point at <hi>Daniels</hi> Weeks, (which led down to him) by the identity of the phraſe, takes a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43449:30"/>Text from <hi>Iſay, He hath annointed me to preach the Goſpel. Luke</hi> 4.18. From whence he raiſeth this ſo uſefull doctrin, (had not his hearers been unimagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſtupid) <hi>This Day is this Scripture fulfild in your ears, verſe</hi> 21. But why (I pray) This Scripture, and this Day? Why? Look in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and you will eaſily ſee the reaſon, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Seventy weeks, &amp;c.— And to anoint the moſt holy. q. d.</hi> The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time leading to me is now expir'd, This Day is this Scripture fulfild in your eares, <hi>The Spirit hath anointed me</hi>— How is it therefore O yee Hypocrites that yee do not diſcern this time? The Lord deliver every one of us from the danger of the like expoſtulation, How is it, &amp;c. Since the <hi>Epocha</hi> guiding us in the <hi>Revelation</hi> to his ſecond coming, is far more cleerly expreſt than that which led to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in <hi>Daniel,</hi> Let any one weigh, <hi>[And when the Dragon ſaw he was caſt unto the Earth, &amp;c.]</hi> with <hi>[Seventy weeks are determind upon thy people and upon thy holy City]</hi> Their <hi>[WHEN]</hi> from whence they were to reckon, ſeemes to be but obſcurely impli'd, ours cleerly expreſt, and yet they were call'd Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, &amp;c. And ſhall not we? God grant we be not.</p>
            <p>I will preſent but one ſuggeſtion more to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and take leave. Is it not probable that the ſubtil old Serpent, about the times in which Chriſt was to be born (of which he was able enough to make collection from <hi>Daniels</hi> Weeks) perceiving the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as I told thee) partly from <hi>Daniel,</hi> and partly from the <hi>Sibyls</hi> ſcatterd predictions, to be full of the expectation of ſome admirable change, thruſt in that marvellous peece of impoſture about <hi>Salonius, Pollio</hi>'s Son, born ſmiling, purpoſely to become the ſubject on whom all thoſe glorious Elogies of happy mutation might be fixt,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Note; This youth came ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lingly into the world, but our Lord with all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, which aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but the Devill made uſe of to apply <hi>[Redeunt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnia regna]</hi> to the me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry Brat, and not to the deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Infant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſiſted to this ſuggeſtion through the temporal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, by the vain hope whereof he had prepar'd the world for this after-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. <hi>ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</hi>
               </note> as his exceeding remarkable manner of coming into the world (ſo quite contrary to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther births) might very ſignificantly portend, in deſign
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43449:30"/>to divert that age from pitching their eyes on the holy Infant Jeſus? <hi>Vid. Elog.</hi> 4. <hi>Virgil.</hi> But wilt thou not marvail if I ſhew thee that the Devill (being loath to uſe any other method than what formerly ſucceeded ſo proſperouſly) ſeeing, (doubtleſs) that his ſecond co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is neer approaching, hath laid the ſame ſnare to divert our Nation from expecting this manner of his appearance, by tempting one <hi>Ariſe Evans</hi> (a man ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry exemplary in having predicted divers things which have anſwerably ſucceeded, and conſequently, authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick enough to be his inſtrument in ſuch a ſnare) to faſten ſeveral preſages concerning the fate of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer King (of pious memory) all which obteind effect, and the reſtitution of this his ſon, upon many paſſages of Scripture that evidently concern this matter, as thou wilt eaſily acknowledge (Reader) if in his Book intitled A voice from Heaven, where thou wilt find great variety from the Bible (belonging to this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery) applied to our ſtate of things partly in what is paſt, partly in what he incourageth us to expect in <hi>England?</hi> In a word, All the glorious promiſes meant in Scripture of our Lord, he applyes to the King of <hi>England</hi> (calling him as I remember the root of <hi>Jeſſe</hi>) and in expreſs termes bids them that expect Chriſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal reign, to look for the accompliſhment of thoſe promiſes in that ſpeculation he acquaints us with about our K. <hi>Charles,</hi> made by him to be the King that ſhall rule in righteouſnes, yea and that man by whom God will Judge the World. <hi>V. pl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider it Reader, and the Lord direct thee.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:43449:31"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>The Holy Trinity, to whom be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting honour, be pleas'd to open our hearts and eyes to the diſcerning this myſtery, and the time leading down unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:43449:31"/>
            <head>The Requeſt of the Author to his Fellow-Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, imploring their ſatisfaction in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing conſiderations.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> SInce by the principles of this Diſcourſe the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd Myſtery (commencing at our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviours coming) begins with <hi>Rome</hi>'s Ruine, (for if She be <hi>Babylon,</hi> her fall (as to the City) is affixt to the very hour of the Witneſſes riſing, being the complete term of the <hi>1260.</hi> Dayes, <hi>Revel. 11.13.</hi>) Whether it be altogether unworthy of our attention to obſerve how full the world is at this very day of expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of that Long'd-for Overthrow, in ſo much that Divers mouths and pens (without any reference at all to the Apocalyps) have publiſht their judgements of that incomparable Deſolation likely to be before <hi>1656.</hi> paſſe over us. Nay more, Is it of no moment that the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire (the Apocalyptical <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates</hi>) is aim'd at by <hi>Gaffarel</hi> about <hi>Anno 1655?</hi> Really, ſuch prognoſtications are wont to affect me as little as moſt men (I perſwade my ſelf) breathing; but in this caſe, where the matter ſeems ſo cleerly pointed at by the ſacred Authority of the Apocalyps, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially their proofs being of a different nature from mine, yet pitching on the ſame term,) I could not but preſent this humble expoſtulation.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Whether the Holy Spirit ſeem not to have (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome peculiar way) determined the badge of the Witneſſes-ſlaughter to be look'l after in <hi>Britain</hi> rather than any other parts of the Reformation; and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Revel. <hi>11.8.</hi> Which we render In the ſtreet, will very Naturally ſignify,<note place="margin">The Adjective (as all will grant) is here put ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</note> In the Latitude (coming from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as every School-boy knows) In the Out-Coaſt, border or Frontier, of the great City, or of the <hi>Roman</hi> Dominions; and in this
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:43449:32"/>ſenſe who ſees not how well it ſuits with the State of <hi>Britain</hi> in thoſe times?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whether thoſe words [were alſo our Lord was Crucified] muſt not needs be underſtood figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? for where Chriſt was really Crucified (viz. <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>) there are (I fear) no Witneſſes to be ſlain, The G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Lording it there; or if there be any poor Chriſtian-Pilgrims, yet are their conditions no harder now than they have been for many hundred yeers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo that this ſlaughter can in no ſenſe be verified of that place at this time: And of the times paſt we have no reaſon to inquire, ſince this paſſage leads down to the Concluſion. Beſides, may not the Word <hi>(Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually)</hi> in the Text, be a Key to open into ſuch an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception? But if ſuch a ſenſe be here allowable, need we go far for the application, if we do but reflect upon the horridneſs of what this laſt age hath been guilty? <hi>The Lords Chriſt</hi> might be Crucified when ſome little dream't on't. <hi>vid. Heb. 6.6.</hi> God (the ſearcher of Hearts) knows how far I am from an Incendiarie's ſpirit in theſe demands, (for how can the grounds upon which this tractate is fram'd poſſibly ſuit with ſuch a deſign?) All my aim is at my own and others ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and watchfulneſs.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſince 'tis Generally granted, that<note n="(*)" place="margin">See his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony in the Diſcourſe.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> (within <hi>30.</hi> yeers of <hi>St. Johns</hi> death,) was ſo firm an aſſertor of the Notion of the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> deliverd in this treatiſe, as likewiſe <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> both which liv'd and convers'd with the Apoſtles immediate Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and peculiarly, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> brought up at <hi>Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi>'s feet, who was <hi>St. Johns</hi> Diſciple, and could relate to <hi>Irenaeus</hi> (as himſelf is known to ſay) what <hi>St. John</hi> was wont to do and ſpeak: I now earneſtly begg of all my fellow Brethren ſeriouſly to conſider, whether it be not more than probable that this very doctrine was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd to them from <hi>St. Johns</hi> own mouth, eſpecially, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43449:32"/>how ſuitable it is to the tenour of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, in which <hi>St. John</hi> was the infallible Spirits Pen-man.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA,</head>
            <p>PAge 2. for Jeſus read Jeruſalem. p. 3. Divers read Divines. p. 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 10. to read too. p. 15. ſtore I uſe read ſtorehouſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
